<seedurl>
	http://www.bbc.com
</seedurl>
<url>
	http://www.bbc.com/news/world-latin-america-35274547
</url>
<title>
	'El Chapo': Mexico signals extradition to US
</title>
<description>
	The Mexican attorney general's office says it will begin the process of extraditing recaptured drug lord Joaquin "El Chapo" Guzman to the US.

It said the move was in line with US extradition requests from 2014.
On Friday Guzman was detained and sent back to the maximum-security prison he escaped from six months ago. 
Guzman, who was one of the world's most wanted drug traffickers, escaped from there in July through a tunnel dug in the showers.
That was his second escape - he was first arrested in Guatemala in 1993 and escaped from Puente Grande jail in 2001, reportedly in a laundry basket after bribing officials.
He was on the run for 13 years before being held again in 2014. 
Previous requests from the US have been turned down.
The Mexican government has clearly decided that it may never be able to hold Joaquin Guzman behind bars.
He has managed to escape from two high-security prisons so far and he is still a man with huge wealth and the capacity to bribe. 
So they have decided to hand him over to the Americans. The US will be keen to glean from Guzman information about his cartel and also about how many Mexican officials he has in his pay. 
The information could be embarrassing to President Enrique Pena Nieto, who has done little to fight corruption in Mexico. But whether Guzman would be prepared to enter into a plea bargain with the Americans remains uncertain.
Who is 'El Chapo' Guzman?
No detail was given about the time frame for an extradition but experts say the process could take months, the BBC's Katy Watson in Mexico City reports.
The attorney general's office said that lawyers for Guzman would have three days to file objections and 20 more days to prove them, though that timeframe could be extended, AFP news agency reports.
In a statement welcoming Guzman's recapture, Attorney General Loretta Lynch said Guzman had caused "significant violence, suffering and corruption on multiple continents".
The US filed requests in 2014 for his extradition so he could face charges of smuggling vast amounts of drugs into the country.
Guzman, who was named Public Enemy Number One by the Chicago Crime Commission in 2013, has been indicted by at least seven US federal district courts.
Guzman was arrested on Friday in the north-western city of Los Mochis in his home state of Sinaloa - which he had come to dominate through his drugs cartel.
During the raid, he managed to flee through a drain but was later caught by marines in a shootout.
Five suspects were killed in the operation and one marine wounded.

</description>
<tags>
	the mexican attorney general's office says it will begin the process of extraditing recaptured drug lord joaquin "el chapo" guzman to the us.
</tags>