<seedurl>
	http://www.bbc.com
</seedurl>
<url>
	http://www.bbc.com/sport/football/35264655
</url>
<title>
	BBC Sport
</title>
<description>
	
For a better experience on your device, try our mobile site.
    Karim Benzema claimed his 100th league goal for the club with an early opener in the first game since the departure of previous manager Rafael Benitez.

    Bale headed the second and found the bottom corner after the break before sealing his treble with another header. 

    Benzema hit a fifth to leave Real two points behind league leaders Barcelona.

    Barca's 
    
comfortable 4-0 victory 

     over Granada put added pressure on Real at the outset, but they responded in style under the guidance of their new boss.

    Not really. When you take over a side that has lost one of its previous nine games, scoring 36 goals in the process, there isn't much need to.

    The 43-year-old gave a low-key acknowledgement to the rapturous welcome received from supporters - a couple of modest waves hinted at the Frenchman's desire not to be the centre of attention. 

    On this occasion his players certainly did all the talking.

    The inclusion of the attack-minded Dani Carvajal in defence as one of two changes hinted at the way Zidane wants his full-backs to get forward more. He was repaid when the right-back, in for Danilo, set up the first of Bale's goals. And it was the kind of line-up the fans wanted to see.  

    As sporting director of Los Blancos, Zidane was instrumental in Welshman Bale's record-breaking £85.3m move to the 
    
Bernabeu from Tottenham 

     in 2013 and he will continue to be a centre-piece of the new manager's plans if he keeps producing displays like this. 

    Bale did not start off too well, and he should have been flagged offside as Benzema claimed Real's first goal. But from that point, the 26-year-old's contribution was wholly positive.

    He departed to a hero's send-off when substituted towards the end, and the look of envy on Cristiano Ronaldo's face conveyed how fine a performance it had been.

    There remains defensive frailties which would have been fully exploited by a better side than Deportivo. 

    The visitors should have taken the lead, and Zidane will have been alarmed at the ease with which his side allowed crosses into their area, especially in the first half. A lack of communication between his centre-backs also needs to be addressed. 

    Of course any side possessing Ronaldo, Bale and Benzema will score goals but, despite the clean sheet, Real continue to look vulnerable at the other end.

    "Whenever you win a match, then the coach can only be happy, and I'm happy. What I liked most of all was the attitude of everyone, those who played and those who didn't. 

    "Winning 5-0 isn't easy against a side like Deportivo and I'm happy with our first game and our first four days of training."

    Real have more than a week to prepare for their next game, when they host struggling Sporting Gijon on 17 January. It's a quicker turnaround for Deportivo, who welcome second-tier side Mirandes in the Copa del Rey on Tuesday, following a 1-1 draw in last week's first leg of the last-16 tie. 

    Foul by Pepe (Real Madrid). 
    Oriol Riera (Deportivo de La Coruña) wins a free kick in the attacking half. 
    Foul by Luka Modric (Real Madrid). 
    Alejandro Arribas (Deportivo de La Coruña) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Attempt missed. Cristiano Ronaldo (Real Madrid) right footed shot from very close range is high and wide to the left. Assisted by Marcelo with a cross. 
    Offside, Deportivo de La Coruña. Oriol Riera tries a through ball, but Luis Alberto is caught offside. 
    Attempt blocked. Jonás Gutiérrez (Deportivo de La Coruña) left footed shot from outside the box is blocked. Assisted by Lucas Pérez. 
    Attempt blocked. James Rodríguez (Real Madrid) left footed shot from outside the box is blocked. 
    Corner,  Real Madrid. Conceded by Luisinho. 
    Attempt blocked. Jesé (Real Madrid) right footed shot from a difficult angle on the right is blocked. Assisted by Daniel Carvajal. 
    Offside, Real Madrid. James Rodríguez tries a through ball, but Cristiano Ronaldo is caught offside. 
    Attempt missed. Juanfran (Deportivo de La Coruña) right footed shot from outside the box is too high following a corner. 
    Corner,  Deportivo de La Coruña. Conceded by Raphael Varane. 
    Attempt missed. Cristiano Ronaldo (Real Madrid) right footed shot from the right side of the box is close, but misses to the left. Assisted by Luka Modric. 
    Attempt blocked. Marcelo (Real Madrid) right footed shot from outside the box is blocked. 
    Attempt missed. Luis Alberto (Deportivo de La Coruña) right footed shot from very close range is high and wide to the right. Assisted by Lucas Pérez with a cross following a corner. 
    Corner,  Deportivo de La Coruña. Conceded by Keylor Navas. 
    Attempt saved. Luis Alberto (Deportivo de La Coruña) right footed shot from outside the box is saved in the bottom right corner. Assisted by Jonás Gutiérrez. 
    Attempt blocked. Luisinho (Deportivo de La Coruña) right footed shot from the left side of the box is blocked. Assisted by Lucas Pérez. 
    Corner,  Deportivo de La Coruña. Conceded by Toni Kroos. 
    Attempt missed. Pedro Mosquera (Deportivo de La Coruña) left footed shot from outside the box is too high. 
    Foul by Jesé (Real Madrid). 
    Luisinho (Deportivo de La Coruña) wins a free kick on the left wing. 
    Offside, Real Madrid. James Rodríguez tries a through ball, but Cristiano Ronaldo is caught offside. 
    Attempt saved. Cristiano Ronaldo (Real Madrid) right footed shot from outside the box is saved in the centre of the goal. Assisted by Karim Benzema. 
    Attempt blocked. Luis Alberto (Deportivo de La Coruña) right footed shot from the centre of the box is blocked. Assisted by Lucas Pérez. 
    Karim Benzema (Real Madrid) wins a free kick on the right wing. 
    Foul by Alejandro Arribas (Deportivo de La Coruña). 
    Attempt missed. Jonás Gutiérrez (Deportivo de La Coruña) right footed shot from outside the box is close, but misses to the right. 
    Offside, Deportivo de La Coruña. Pedro Mosquera tries a through ball, but Oriol Riera is caught offside. 
    Pepe (Real Madrid) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Foul by Oriol Riera (Deportivo de La Coruña). 
    Attempt missed. Gareth Bale (Real Madrid) left footed shot from outside the box is high and wide to the left. Assisted by Daniel Carvajal. 
    Cristiano Ronaldo (Real Madrid) wins a free kick in the attacking half. 
    Pedro Mosquera (Deportivo de La Coruña). 
    Corner,  Real Madrid. Conceded by Sidnei. 
    Attempt missed. Cristiano Ronaldo (Real Madrid) left footed shot from outside the box is high and wide to the left. 
    Toni Kroos (Real Madrid) wins a free kick in the attacking half. 
    Foul by Lucas Pérez (Deportivo de La Coruña). 
    Foul by Gareth Bale (Real Madrid). 
    Sidnei (Deportivo de La Coruña) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Attempt blocked. Álex Bergantiños (Deportivo de La Coruña) right footed shot from outside the box is blocked. Assisted by Luis Alberto. 
    Corner,  Deportivo de La Coruña. Conceded by Pepe. 
    Toni Kroos (Real Madrid) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Foul by Pedro Mosquera (Deportivo de La Coruña). 
    Attempt saved. Cristiano Ronaldo (Real Madrid) right footed shot from outside the box is saved in the bottom left corner. Assisted by Toni Kroos. 
    Luka Modric (Real Madrid) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Foul by Pedro Mosquera (Deportivo de La Coruña). 
    Corner,  Deportivo de La Coruña. Conceded by Daniel Carvajal. 
    Attempt missed. Cristiano Ronaldo (Real Madrid) right footed shot from the left side of the box is just a bit too high. Assisted by Marcelo. 
    Isco (Real Madrid) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Foul by Álex Bergantiños (Deportivo de La Coruña). 
    Attempt missed. Luis Alberto (Deportivo de La Coruña) right footed shot from outside the box is just a bit too high. Assisted by Faycal Fajr. 
    Attempt saved. Karim Benzema (Real Madrid) left footed shot from the left side of the box is saved in the bottom right corner. Assisted by Gareth Bale. 
    Marcelo (Real Madrid) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Foul by Fede Cartabia (Deportivo de La Coruña). 
    Cristiano Ronaldo (Real Madrid) hits the left post with a header from the centre of the box. Assisted by Gareth Bale. 
    Attempt missed. Lucas Pérez (Deportivo de La Coruña) left footed shot from outside the box is close, but misses to the left. Assisted by Álex Bergantiños. 
    Attempt missed. Lucas Pérez (Deportivo de La Coruña) left footed shot from outside the box is close, but misses to the right. Assisted by Fede Cartabia. 
    Foul by Daniel Carvajal (Real Madrid). 
    Faycal Fajr (Deportivo de La Coruña) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Attempt missed. Lucas Pérez (Deportivo de La Coruña) left footed shot from the left side of the box is high and wide to the left. Assisted by Álex Bergantiños. 
    Foul by Toni Kroos (Real Madrid). 
    Fede Cartabia (Deportivo de La Coruña) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Corner,  Deportivo de La Coruña. Conceded by Gareth Bale. 
    Corner,  Deportivo de La Coruña. Conceded by Sergio Ramos. 
    Offside, Real Madrid. Luka Modric tries a through ball, but Cristiano Ronaldo is caught offside. 
    Attempt missed. Cristiano Ronaldo (Real Madrid) right footed shot from the left side of the box is close, but misses to the right. Assisted by Marcelo. 
    Attempt saved. Fede Cartabia (Deportivo de La Coruña) left footed shot from outside the box is saved in the bottom right corner. Assisted by Pedro Mosquera. 
    Foul by Toni Kroos (Real Madrid). 
    Fede Cartabia (Deportivo de La Coruña) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Attempt missed. Marcelo (Real Madrid) left footed shot from the centre of the box is close, but misses to the left. Assisted by Isco. 
    Foul by Karim Benzema (Real Madrid). 
    Pedro Mosquera (Deportivo de La Coruña) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Corner,  Real Madrid. Conceded by Fernando Navarro. 
    Attempt blocked. Sergio Ramos (Real Madrid) right footed shot from the centre of the box is blocked. Assisted by Karim Benzema with a headed pass. 
    Corner,  Real Madrid. Conceded by Alejandro Arribas. 
    Attempt blocked. Cristiano Ronaldo (Real Madrid) right footed shot from outside the box is blocked. Assisted by Isco. 
    Attempt missed. Karim Benzema (Real Madrid) header from the centre of the box is high and wide to the left. Assisted by Marcelo with a cross. 
    Corner,  Deportivo de La Coruña. Conceded by Keylor Navas. 
    Attempt saved. Lucas Pérez (Deportivo de La Coruña) right footed shot from the centre of the box is saved in the centre of the goal. Assisted by Pedro Mosquera with a through ball. 
    Corner,  Deportivo de La Coruña. Conceded by Pepe. 
    Attempt blocked. Luis Alberto (Deportivo de La Coruña) right footed shot from outside the box is blocked. Assisted by Lucas Pérez. 
    Corner,  Real Madrid. Conceded by Germán Lux. 
    Attempt saved. Cristiano Ronaldo (Real Madrid) left footed shot from outside the box is saved in the bottom left corner. Assisted by Karim Benzema. 
    Attempt saved. Faycal Fajr (Deportivo de La Coruña) right footed shot from a difficult angle and long range on the left is saved in the centre of the goal. Assisted by Juanfran with a cross. 
    Attempt missed. Luis Alberto (Deportivo de La Coruña) right footed shot from outside the box is high and wide to the right. Assisted by Lucas Pérez. 
    Foul by Isco (Real Madrid). 
    Fede Cartabia (Deportivo de La Coruña) wins a free kick on the right wing. 
    Lineups are announced and players are warming up. 
Copyright © 2015 BBC. The BBC is not responsible for the content of external sites. Read more.
This page is best viewed in an up-to-date web browser with style sheets (CSS) enabled. While you will be able to view the content of this page in your current browser, you will not be able to get the full visual experience. Please consider upgrading your browser software or enabling style sheets (CSS) if you are able to do so.

</description>
<tags>
	
</tags>