<seedurl>
	http://www.bbc.com
</seedurl>
<url>
	http://www.bbc.com/sport/football/35264648
</url>
<title>
	BBC Sport
</title>
<description>
	
For a better experience on your device, try our mobile site.
    The Argentine scored twice in the first 15 minutes and added another after the break to take his season's tally to 18, as Barca made it 20 games unbeaten. 

    Messi put Barcelona in command with composed close-range finishes to Luis Suarez-inspired moves.

    He followed up to add a 58th-minute third, before Neymar lobbed the fourth.

    Victory increased Barcelona's advantage over Real Madrid to five points - the side from the Spanish capital host Deportivo La Coruna in 
    
Zinedine Zidane's first game 

     in charge later on Saturday.

    Barca's hold on top spot could be short-lived as they will surrender their position if Atletico win at Celta Vigo on Sunday.

    Messi broke the deadlock in the eighth minute against a side who were beaten 6-0 at the Nou Camp last season. 

    A clever dummy from Suarez allowed league debutant Arda Turan to thread a fine ball to the Argentine to slot home.

    The second came six minutes later, as Neymar eased through before passing to Suarez, who knocked the ball down for Messi to finish.

    Granada came into the contest more in the second half, with striker Isaac Success posing a threat, and David Lomban hooking a chance over the bar.

    Normal service was soon resumed however, as Messi claimed his third - and 11th goal in eight La Liga appearances against Granada - following up after a dummy by Turan let in Neymar to shoot against the frame of the goal.

    Neymar capped another impressive individual display by adding a fourth goal with seven minutes left thanks to a precise lob after good work by Messi and Suarez.

     Barcelona boss Luis Enrique:

     "I made some changes now when I can and I have the chance to share out the burden. 

    "The key will be to get to the matches in a couple of months feeling fresh.

    "I'm very satisfied with how the team played. Everybody was focused from the beginning and the players knew how important it was to win these three points."

    Attempt saved. Javi Márquez (Granada CF) left footed shot from outside the box is saved in the bottom right corner. 
    Foul by Adriano (Barcelona). 
    Robert Ibáñez (Granada CF) wins a free kick in the attacking half. 
    Thomas Vermaelen (Barcelona) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Foul by Success (Granada CF). 
    Foul by Dani Alves (Barcelona). 
    Robert Ibáñez (Granada CF) wins a free kick on the left wing. 
    Foul by Adriano (Barcelona). 
    Rubén Pérez (Granada CF) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Ivan Rakitic (Barcelona) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Foul by Cristiano Biraghi (Granada CF). 
    Attempt missed. Luis Suárez (Barcelona) left footed shot from outside the box is too high. 
    Attempt missed. Neymar (Barcelona) right footed shot from the left side of the box is high and wide to the right. Assisted by Adriano. 
    Offside, Granada CF. Robert Ibáñez tries a through ball, but Javi Márquez is caught offside. 
    Luis Suárez (Barcelona) wins a free kick on the left wing. 
    Foul by Edgar Méndez (Granada CF). 
    Adriano (Barcelona) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Foul by Uche (Granada CF). 
    Foul by Arda Turan (Barcelona). 
    Rubén Rochina (Granada CF) wins a free kick in the attacking half. 
    Attempt saved. Rubén Rochina (Granada CF) left footed shot from the left side of the box is saved in the centre of the goal. Assisted by Cristiano Biraghi. 
    Neymar (Barcelona) wins a free kick on the left wing. 
    Foul by Rubén Rochina (Granada CF). 
    Foul by Aleix Vidal (Barcelona). 
    Success (Granada CF) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Corner,  Barcelona. Conceded by Lombán. 
    Attempt blocked. Lionel Messi (Barcelona) left footed shot from long range on the right is blocked. 
    Aleix Vidal (Barcelona) wins a free kick on the right wing. 
    Foul by Doria (Granada CF). 
    Offside, Granada CF. Cristiano Biraghi tries a through ball, but Success is caught offside. 
    Attempt saved. Neymar (Barcelona) right footed shot from a difficult angle on the left is saved in the centre of the goal. Assisted by Sergi Roberto with a through ball. 
    Neymar (Barcelona) wins a free kick in the attacking half. 
    Foul by Lombán (Granada CF). 
    Jordi Alba (Barcelona) wins a free kick on the left wing. 
    Foul by Edgar Méndez (Granada CF). 
    Neymar (Barcelona) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Foul by Edgar Méndez (Granada CF). 
    Attempt saved. Lombán (Granada CF) right footed shot from outside the box is saved in the centre of the goal. 
    Foul by Aleix Vidal (Barcelona). 
    Adalberto Peñaranda (Granada CF) wins a free kick in the attacking half. 
    Attempt missed. Lombán (Granada CF) right footed shot from the centre of the box is just a bit too high. Assisted by Adalberto Peñaranda with a headed pass following a set piece situation. 
    Foul by Thomas Vermaelen (Barcelona). 
    Success (Granada CF) wins a free kick on the right wing. 
    Attempt saved. Success (Granada CF) left footed shot from outside the box is saved in the centre of the goal. Assisted by Edgar Méndez. 
    Foul by Ivan Rakitic (Barcelona). 
    Adalberto Peñaranda (Granada CF) wins a free kick on the left wing. 
    Attempt saved. Arda Turan (Barcelona) right footed shot from the left side of the box is saved in the centre of the goal. Assisted by Neymar. 
    Attempt missed. Rubén Rochina (Granada CF) left footed shot from outside the box is close, but misses to the right. Assisted by Success. 
    Attempt missed. Neymar (Barcelona) left footed shot from the left side of the box is close, but misses to the left. Assisted by Ivan Rakitic. 
    Foul by Sergi Roberto (Barcelona). 
    Success (Granada CF) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Neymar (Barcelona) wins a free kick on the left wing. 
    Foul by Uche (Granada CF). 
    Corner,  Barcelona. Conceded by Doria. 
    Lionel Messi (Barcelona) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Foul by Lombán (Granada CF). 
    Attempt missed. Ivan Rakitic (Barcelona) right footed shot from outside the box is high and wide to the right. Assisted by Sergi Roberto. 
    Attempt missed. Neymar (Barcelona) right footed shot from the centre of the box is high and wide to the right. 
    Foul by Ivan Rakitic (Barcelona). 
    Rubén Rochina (Granada CF) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Offside, Barcelona. Neymar tries a through ball, but Luis Suárez is caught offside. 
    Arda Turan (Barcelona) wins a free kick in the attacking half. 
    Foul by Adalberto Peñaranda (Granada CF). 
    Attempt blocked. Rubén Pérez (Granada CF) right footed shot from outside the box is blocked. Assisted by Rubén Rochina. 
    Dangerous play by Arda Turan (Barcelona). 
    Rene Krhin (Granada CF) wins a free kick in the attacking half. 
    Attempt saved. Lionel Messi (Barcelona) left footed shot from the centre of the box is saved in the centre of the goal. Assisted by Aleix Vidal. 
    Ivan Rakitic (Barcelona) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Foul by Rubén Rochina (Granada CF). 
    Offside, Granada CF. Cristiano Biraghi tries a through ball, but Success is caught offside. 
    Attempt missed. Luis Suárez (Barcelona) right footed shot from more than 35 yards misses to the left. Assisted by Sergi Roberto. 
    Foul by Arda Turan (Barcelona). 
    Rubén Rochina (Granada CF) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Attempt missed. Luis Suárez (Barcelona) left footed shot from the centre of the box is close, but misses to the left. Assisted by Neymar. 
    Corner,  Barcelona. Conceded by Uche. 
    Corner,  Barcelona. Conceded by Edgar Méndez. 
    Arda Turan (Barcelona) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Foul by Edgar Méndez (Granada CF). 
    Foul by Sergi Roberto (Barcelona). 
    Rubén Rochina (Granada CF) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Foul by Jordi Alba (Barcelona). 
    Edgar Méndez (Granada CF) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Sergi Roberto (Barcelona) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Foul by Rubén Pérez (Granada CF). 
    Neymar (Barcelona) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Foul by Rubén Rochina (Granada CF). 
    Sergi Roberto (Barcelona) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Foul by Rubén Rochina (Granada CF). 
    Corner,  Barcelona. Conceded by Andrés Fernández. 
    Thomas Vermaelen (Barcelona) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Foul by Adalberto Peñaranda (Granada CF). 
    Corner,  Barcelona. Conceded by Andrés Fernández. 
    Attempt saved. Jordi Alba (Barcelona) left footed shot from the centre of the box is saved in the bottom left corner. Assisted by Lionel Messi with a through ball. 
    Ivan Rakitic (Barcelona) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Foul by Rubén Pérez (Granada CF). 
    Attempt missed. Ivan Rakitic (Barcelona) right footed shot from the right side of the box misses to the left. Assisted by Gerard Piqué. 
    Corner,  Barcelona. Conceded by Lombán. 
    Attempt missed. Rubén Rochina (Granada CF) left footed shot from outside the box is too high. 
    Lineups are announced and players are warming up. 
Copyright © 2015 BBC. The BBC is not responsible for the content of external sites. Read more.
This page is best viewed in an up-to-date web browser with style sheets (CSS) enabled. While you will be able to view the content of this page in your current browser, you will not be able to get the full visual experience. Please consider upgrading your browser software or enabling style sheets (CSS) if you are able to do so.

</description>
<tags>
	
</tags>