<seedurl>
	http://www.bbc.com
</seedurl>
<url>
	http://www.bbc.com/sport/football/35211388
</url>
<title>
	Wycombe Wanderers 1-1 Aston Villa
</title>
<description>
	
For a better experience on your device, try our mobile site.
    Remi Garde looks certain to preside over Villa's relegation to the Championship - and both the manager and his players felt the fury of many travelling supporters at the final whistle, with captain Micah Richards involved in heated exchanges with fans at the end.

    Richards gave Villa the lead after 22 minutes with a low right-foot shot but Wycombe, sixth in League Two and FA Cup semi-finalists in 2001, were level five minutes after half-time through Joe Jacobson's penalty.

    Villa were furious referee Michael Oliver punished Ashley Westwood for his clash with Matt Bloomfield - and their frustration increased when Rudy Gestede's deflected late shot bounced off the bar.


Reaction to Saturday's FA Cup third-round games

    Garde avoided the humiliation of defeat by League Two opposition - but he is still without a win 10 games after succeeding Tim Sherwood.

    There will be an element of relief but also frustration that a decent first-half display did not bring more reward than Richards' goal.

    It gave Wycombe hope and they cashed in with a contentious penalty from Jacobson - although the flailing arm of Westwood was asking for trouble.

    Villa's failure to win simply confirms the deeper malaise at Villa Park, and the fact Garde has inherited a desperately poor squad that does not look like it has what it takes to mount the sort of miracle recovery they will need to stay in the Premier League.

    Garde must now try to work the markets in January to put together an unlikely escape plan, but the fact not too many would have regarded a Wycombe win as a huge shock tells you just how dismal this Villa squad is.

    This was a day that had all the ingredients that make up a classic FA Cup cocktail - a Premier League side in crisis, a club 54 places below them on the ladder and a biblical storm hitting the ground before kick-off just to make conditions even more hazardous.

    The League Two side were perfect hosts as the media descended on Buckinghamshire - in search of a shock, it must be admitted - as Adams Park was packed to its 9,000 capacity - one man interrupting walking his dog for a full 20 minutes during the first half to take in the action on a hill high behind one end of the ground.

    As Wycombe's fans made their way around the steep hills and into the stadium, there was an anticipation that made this day the epitome of what still makes the FA Cup special.

    The home side did not get the win they would have craved but they still earned a lucrative replay with a spirited second-half display and did themselves proud on and off the field.

    The 2,500 Villa fans who made the short journey down the M40 seem resigned to relegation this season as they are cut off at the bottom of the Premier League - but they retain some dark humour.

    There was anger among their number as they sang "We want our Villa back" moments into the game, understandable with owner Randy Lerner having failed to sell the club and presided over a decline that looks certain to end in the Championship.

    Chants of "You don't know what you're doing" came when Garde put Jordan Veretout on for Carles Gil after 71 minutes.

    And there was hostility at the final whistle when fans sang "You're not fit to wear the shirt" in the direction of Villa's players as they trooped off.

    There was also the sight of captain and goalscorer Richards in heated debate with disappointed fans at the final whistle. Villa is a club in freefall.

    But there was humour, too, to sustain Villa's followers.

    When a group of flag-bearing children walked behind the goal where Villa's supporters were gathered, they were greeted by chants of "Sign them up, sign them up" before breaking into an chorus of "We're down and we know we are".

    Richards lifted the spirits with a first-half strike and, amid the celebrations, they sang "We've scored a goal" before taunting Wycombe fans for supporting a team actually losing to Villa.

    In their defence, Villa's fans gave tremendous support to a team that is so clearly short of any serious quality, although a few expressed their hostility at the failure to beat lowly Wycombe when the final whistle sounded.

    It appears they have decided it is better to laugh than cry at their plight.

    Corner,  Aston Villa. Conceded by Anthony Stewart. 
    Kieran Richardson (Aston Villa) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Foul by Michael Harriman (Wycombe Wanderers). 
    Attempt missed. Sam Wood (Wycombe Wanderers) left footed shot from outside the box misses to the right. 
    Leandro Bacuna (Aston Villa) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Foul by Gozie Ugwu (Wycombe Wanderers). 
    Jordan Lyden (Aston Villa) wins a free kick in the attacking half. 
    Foul by Stephen McGinn (Wycombe Wanderers). 
    Attempt saved. Idrissa Gueye (Aston Villa) right footed shot from outside the box is saved in the centre of the goal. Assisted by Rudy Gestede. 
    Offside, Wycombe Wanderers. Michael Harriman tries a through ball, but Garry Thompson is caught offside. 
    Attempt missed. Jordan Ayew (Aston Villa) header from the right side of the six yard box is high and wide to the right. Assisted by Jordan Veretout with a cross following a corner. 
    Corner,  Aston Villa. Conceded by Jason McCarthy. 
    Attempt blocked. Rudy Gestede (Aston Villa) header from the centre of the box is blocked. Assisted by Jordan Veretout with a cross. 
    Corner,  Aston Villa. Conceded by Anthony Stewart. 
    Attempt blocked. Rudy Gestede (Aston Villa) right footed shot from outside the box is blocked. Assisted by Kieran Richardson. 
    Attempt missed. Jordan Ayew (Aston Villa) right footed shot from the right side of the box is close, but misses to the left. Assisted by Idrissa Gueye. 
    Attempt missed. Rudy Gestede (Aston Villa) right footed shot from the centre of the box is close, but misses the top right corner. Assisted by Leandro Bacuna with a cross following a corner. 
    Corner,  Aston Villa. Conceded by Joe Jacobson. 
    Attempt blocked. Leandro Bacuna (Aston Villa) right footed shot from the right side of the box is blocked. Assisted by Idrissa Gueye. 
    Attempt missed. Micah Richards (Aston Villa) header from the centre of the box misses to the right. Assisted by Jordan Veretout with a cross following a corner. 
    Corner,  Aston Villa. Conceded by Jason McCarthy. 
    Idrissa Gueye (Aston Villa) wins a free kick on the right wing. 
    Foul by Luke O'Nien (Wycombe Wanderers). 
    Attempt missed. Anthony Stewart (Wycombe Wanderers) header from the centre of the box is too high. Assisted by Joe Jacobson with a cross following a set piece situation. 
    Foul by Jores Okore (Aston Villa). 
    Garry Thompson (Wycombe Wanderers) wins a free kick on the left wing. 
    Attempt blocked. Scott Sinclair (Aston Villa) left footed shot from the centre of the box is blocked. Assisted by Micah Richards. 
    Carles Gil (Aston Villa) wins a free kick in the attacking half. 
    Foul by Matt Bloomfield (Wycombe Wanderers). 
    Corner,  Wycombe Wanderers. Conceded by Idrissa Gueye. 
    Rudy Gestede (Aston Villa) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Foul by Aaron Pierre (Wycombe Wanderers). 
    Mark Bunn (Aston Villa) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Foul by Aaron Pierre (Wycombe Wanderers). 
    Corner,  Wycombe Wanderers. Conceded by Ciaran Clark. 
    Foul by Idrissa Gueye (Aston Villa). 
    Matt Bloomfield (Wycombe Wanderers) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Attempt saved. Leandro Bacuna (Aston Villa) right footed shot from outside the box is saved in the bottom left corner. 
    Carles Gil (Aston Villa) wins a free kick in the attacking half. 
    Foul by Joe Jacobson (Wycombe Wanderers). 
    Delay over. They are ready to continue. 
    Delay in match Micah Richards (Aston Villa) because of an injury. 
    Micah Richards (Aston Villa) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Foul by Aaron Holloway (Wycombe Wanderers). 
    Attempt blocked. Sam Wood (Wycombe Wanderers) left footed shot from the left side of the box is blocked. Assisted by Garry Thompson with a cross. 
    Penalty conceded by Ashley Westwood (Aston Villa) after a foul in the penalty area. 
    Penalty Wycombe Wanderers. Matt Bloomfield draws a foul in the penalty area. 
    Attempt missed. Matt Bloomfield (Wycombe Wanderers) header from the centre of the box is close, but misses to the right. Assisted by Michael Harriman with a headed pass. 
    Rudy Gestede (Aston Villa) wins a free kick on the left wing. 
    Foul by Anthony Stewart (Wycombe Wanderers). 
    Carles Gil (Aston Villa) wins a free kick on the right wing. 
    Foul by Sam Wood (Wycombe Wanderers). 
    Attempt blocked. Idrissa Gueye (Aston Villa) right footed shot from outside the box is blocked. Assisted by Leandro Bacuna. 
    Attempt blocked. Carles Gil (Aston Villa) left footed shot from the right side of the box is blocked. Assisted by Leandro Bacuna. 
    Offside, Wycombe Wanderers. Aaron Holloway tries a through ball, but Michael Harriman is caught offside. 
    Attempt missed. Aaron Pierre (Wycombe Wanderers) header from very close range is too high. Assisted by Joe Jacobson with a cross following a corner. 
    Corner,  Wycombe Wanderers. Conceded by Ashley Westwood. 
    Attempt missed. Rudy Gestede (Aston Villa) header from the centre of the box misses to the right. Assisted by Leandro Bacuna with a cross following a corner. 
    Corner,  Aston Villa. Conceded by Jason McCarthy. 
    Offside, Aston Villa. Leandro Bacuna tries a through ball, but Scott Sinclair is caught offside. 
    Foul by Idrissa Gueye (Aston Villa). 
    Sam Wood (Wycombe Wanderers) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Attempt missed. Sam Wood (Wycombe Wanderers) right footed shot from the centre of the box is too high. Assisted by Matt Bloomfield with a cross. 
    Corner,  Wycombe Wanderers. Conceded by Jores Okore. 
    Offside, Wycombe Wanderers. Alexander Lynch tries a through ball, but Garry Thompson is caught offside. 
    Corner,  Wycombe Wanderers. Conceded by Ciaran Clark. 
    Scott Sinclair (Aston Villa) wins a free kick in the attacking half. 
    Foul by Matt Bloomfield (Wycombe Wanderers). 
    Delay over. They are ready to continue. 
    Delay in match Micah Richards (Aston Villa) because of an injury. 
    Attempt blocked. Leandro Bacuna (Aston Villa) left footed shot from outside the box is blocked. Assisted by Rudy Gestede. 
    Offside, Wycombe Wanderers. Jason McCarthy tries a through ball, but Aaron Holloway is caught offside. 
    Attempt saved. Scott Sinclair (Aston Villa) right footed shot from outside the box is saved in the bottom left corner. Assisted by Idrissa Gueye. 
    Attempt missed. Ashley Westwood (Aston Villa) right footed shot from outside the box misses to the right. 
    Attempt blocked. Idrissa Gueye (Aston Villa) left footed shot from outside the box is blocked. Assisted by Ashley Westwood. 
    Jores Okore (Aston Villa) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Foul by Aaron Holloway (Wycombe Wanderers). 
    Attempt missed. Sam Wood (Wycombe Wanderers) left footed shot from the left side of the box misses to the right. Assisted by Matt Bloomfield with a through ball. 
    Jores Okore (Aston Villa) wins a free kick in the defensive half. 
    Foul by Garry Thompson (Wycombe Wanderers). 
    Offside, Wycombe Wanderers. Michael Harriman tries a through ball, but Aaron Holloway is caught offside. 
    Micah Richards (Aston Villa) wins a free kick on the right wing. 
    Foul by Sam Wood (Wycombe Wanderers). 
    Attempt missed. Garry Thompson (Wycombe Wanderers) right footed shot from the left side of the six yard box is close, but misses to the left following a corner. 
    Corner,  Wycombe Wanderers. Conceded by Kieran Richardson. 
    Corner,  Aston Villa. Conceded by Sam Wood. 
    Lineups are announced and players are warming up. 
Copyright © 2015 BBC. The BBC is not responsible for the content of external sites. Read more.
This page is best viewed in an up-to-date web browser with style sheets (CSS) enabled. While you will be able to view the content of this page in your current browser, you will not be able to get the full visual experience. Please consider upgrading your browser software or enabling style sheets (CSS) if you are able to do so.

</description>
<tags>
	
</tags>