<seedurl>
	http://www.bbc.com
</seedurl>
<url>
	http://www.bbc.com/autos/story/20160107-jaguars-xf-goes-from-also-ran-to-frontrunner
</url>
<title>
	From also-ran to frontrunner
</title>
<description>
	
In the years since the comely Jaguar XF debuted in 2007, the car has existed as something of a contrarian’s choice. It has been less a legitimate rival to the Mercedes E-Class, BMW 5-series and Audi A6 than an antidote to the ubiquity of those cars in certain circles. With the debut of the new 2016 XF, Jaguar aims to change that.














 




What looks like a tasteful revision to the undeniably lovely first-generation XF is, in fact, an entirely new car: The new XF shares no sheet metal with the outgoing model. Nothing. It’s the last of the Jaguar line to benefit from aluminium-intensive construction, and the new structure is 75% made of the stuff. Weight has been cut by 11% but rigidity is improved by an impressive 28%. The new car is no longer end-to-end than the old one (fractionally shorter, in fact), but the wheelbase has grown by two inches — space that is put to good use in the passenger compartment. The drag coefficient drops from 0.29 to a very slippery 0.26. Progress.
On the road, the new XF is quick and quiet, and it drives a good deal smaller than it is. Engine choices include the same supercharged 3-litre V6 as the F-Type, tuned to 340- or 380-horsepower and matched to an 8-speed automatic transmission. Rear-wheel drive is standard, but Jaguar’s excellent rear-biased all-wheel-drive system is available. In the US, a 2-litre turbocharged four-cylinder diesel engine — producing 180 horsepower and a hefty 317 pound-feet of torque — arrives mid-year.
From the driver’s seat, the cabin’s lines are sleek and the materials consistently luxurious, with seemingly hundreds of comfort, information and entertainment gewgaws hidden elegantly away when not needed. Safety tech includes cameras that monitor traffic signs, autonomous emergency braking, lane-assist technology, heads-up display, and even sensors that will warn you of vehicles approaching quickly from behind —though if you’re getting passed, you may be doing it wrong.
All of this amounts to a car whose virtues match — and even surpass — those of its German rivals. Formerly a car whose chief attraction was being different, the XF has become a car whose chief attraction is being better.
If you would like to comment on this or anything else you have seen on BBC Autos, head over to our Facebook page or message us on Twitter.




</description>
<tags>
	it,may,look,like,a,mild,revision,of,the,undeniably,lovely,original,,but,the,2016,xf,is,an,entirely,new,—,and,dramatically,better,—,car.,bbc,autos',david,k,gibson,takes,the,wheel.
</tags>