<seedurl>
	http://www.bbc.com
</seedurl>
<url>
	http://www.bbcamerica.com/shows/orphan-black/contest?utm_source=bbc.com&utm_medium=promo%20module&utm_campaign=Channel%20Module
</url>
<title>
	Contest | Orphan Black | BBC America
</title>
<description>
	BBC America and Entertainment Weekly can’t wait to see what you’ve created! Only five (5) unique entries allowed per email address. For questions about what you can submit and specs, refer to the FAQ.
Submission files max size is 10MB for all submissions (plus make sure you keep higher res versions in case you win).
The contest will open on 1/8/2016 at 10:00AM.
This contest is closed, but you can continue to share your fan art on Instagram, Twitter, and Tumblr with #OrphanBlackPoster.
(we’ll also add new season tune-in once that’s announced in mid-January)
There seems to be a glitch in the system! 
Your file may have been too large – please try re-uploading and remember submission files max file size is 10MB for all files.
Or you’ve entered too many times (we love that you love creating Orphan Black fan art but unfortunately you can only submit five times for this contest). 
If you still need help please contact social@bbcamerica.com.
BBC America and Entertainment Weekly received your entry in the Orphan Black Season 4 Fan Art Poster Contest, and — dare we say — Felix would be so proud. 
You’re allowed up to five (5) entries total, so keep ‘em coming. The contest ends Monday February 15th at 11:59 p.m. ET and the winner will be contacted by end of February, 2016. 
And don’t forget to share your entries on Instagram, Twitter, Facebook, and Tumblr with #OrphanBlackPoster.
NO PURCHASE NECESSARY.  Ends on 2/15/16.  Open to legal residents of the 50 US & DC who are 18 years of age or older and the age of majority in their state of residence at the time of entry.  Subject to full Official Rules available here. Void where prohibited.
Don't see your provider? Sign up to be notified when yours is added.
To watch full episodes, you must have a cable provider that supports BBC America's full episode service and you must have BBC America as part of your cable package.
Your account has been deactivated.
Are you sure you want to deactivate your account? You will no longer have access to your profile.
A verification email has been sent, please verify your account to post comments.
An email has been sent with instructions for resetting your password. If you do not see it in your inbox, please check your junk or spam folder.
Don't see your provider? Sign up to be notified when yours is added.
To watch full episodes, you must have a cable provider that supports BBC America's full episode service and you must have BBC America as part of your cable package.
Check your email for link to verify your account.
We've sent an email with instructions to create a new password. Your existing password has not been changed.
We didn't recognize that password reset code. Enter your email address to get a new one.
Password has been successfully updated.
Thank you for verifiying your email address.
You must verify your account in order to post comments. Please enter your email address and you'll receive a verification link to proceed.

</description>
<tags>
	submit your entry to the orphan black season 4 fan poster contest bbc america and entertainment weekly can’t wait to see what you’ve created!...
</tags>