<seedurl>
	http://www.bbc.com
</seedurl>
<url>
	http://www.bbc.com/earth/story/20160108-a-view-of-earth-like-no-other
</url>
<title>
	Art from afar: 17 incredible images from Google Earth
</title>
<description>
	
Misty white dissolves into streaks of grey. Turquoise weaves through a background of tan and black.
Modern art? Or a view of our planet like no other, taken from thousands of miles up.
These beautiful, at times abstract, images are the work of Google Earth View, a collection of the most striking landscape photographs taken by Google Earth satellites (with a little colour enhancement).
Here are 17 of our favourites:


        View image of Nor Lípez, Bolivia (Credit: Google Earth)
    


        View image of Lake Baskunchak is a salt lake in Astrakhan Oblast, Russia (Credit: Google Earth)
    


        View image of Andamooka is known for its opal mining (Credit: Google Earth)
    


        View image of Mansel Island (Credit: Google Earth)
    


        View image of Kiribati (Credit: Google Earth)
    


        View image of Olive groves in Estepa, Spain (Credit: Google Earth)
    


        View image of Al-Hasa (Credit: Google Earth)
    


        View image of Guerrero Negro (Credit: Google Earth)
    


        View image of Patterns in the desert at Boutilimit, Mauritania (Credit: Google Earth)
    


        View image of South Bay, New Zealand. Famed spot for whale watching (Credit: Google Earth)
    


        View image of Home to the Lake District, Cumbria (Credit: Google Earth)
    


        View image of The Andes in Argentina (Credit: Google Earth)
    


        View image of Pico del Teide Spain (Credit: Google Earth)
    


        View image of Mahajanga, a popular tourist destination in Madagascar (Credit: Google Earth)
    


        View image of Nukufetau atoll near Lafanga islet, Tuvalu (Credit: Google Earth)
    


        View image of The village of Chaurikharka, Nepal (Credit: Google Earth)
    


        View image of Lake Acraman  South Australia (Credit: Google Earth)
    




</description>
<tags>
	from,the,lake,district,in,england,to,the,desert,of,saudi,arabia,,see,familiar,places,as,never,before,in,these,satellite,images
</tags>