<seedurl>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us
</seedurl>
<url>
	http://www.theguardian.com/science/2016/jan/08/pluto-new-horizons-photos-nasa-sputnik-planum
</url>
<title>
	New Horizon's latest photos of Pluto: 'This part acts like a lava lamp'
</title>
<description>
	The historic mission sent Nasa its highest-resolution images Thursday of dwarf planet’s Sputnik Planum, a region of pitted plains and a strange ‘X’ formationIcy, pitted plains and craters full of a red soot dot the landscapes of Nasa’s newest photos of Pluto, released late on Thursday.New Horizons, the first spacecraft to ever reach Pluto in a historic mission last year, sent Nasa its highest-resolution photographs so far from the broad, rolling plains that drape the dwarf planet in a heart-shaped expanse. Nasa scientists have dubbed the region within the heart Sputnik Planum, after the first manmade satellite into space. The new images show that the low-lying surface is not totally flat, but rather a mix of pitted areas, 10 to 25 miles wide, that the researchers call “cells”. The cells have ridged margins and raised centers, visible thanks to shadows cast by a low sun, and some cells appear separated by trench or canal formations.Researchers believed the strange surface patterns are formed by convection, as soft frozen nitrogen carries warm ice on to Pluto’s surface, where it evaporates en route to the edge of each cell. Liquid nitrogen may flow beneath the plains, emerging in rivers and moving the glaciers of nitrogen ice above.“This part of Pluto is acting like a lava lamp,” said William McKinnon, deputy lead of the New Horizons geology and geophysics team. “If you can imagine a lava lamp as wide as, and even deeper than, the Hudson Bay.”The “X” formation visible in one photo of the plains is probably the “quadruple junction of former convection cells”, New Horizons’ planetary astronomer Alex Parker tweeted.The darker patches scattered across the plain are probably chunks of dirty water icebergs floating in the denser nitrogen, the researchers said. They added that the pits are probably the results of sublimation, the direct transformation of solid ices to gas. The scientists believe Pluto has a reservoir of solid nitrogen that may be several miles deep. From deep inside Pluto, a small amount of radioactive decay warms the dwarf planet, enough to lift the nitrogen up before it cools and falls for the cycle to begin again.From another region, the reddish, cratered area called Viking Terra, New Horizons has relayed photos that show features smaller than half a city block. In this area scientists have detected methane ices girdled round crater rims, as well as the accumulation of reddish brown tholins, tar-like particles which created reactions involving methane, nitrogen and the sun’s ultraviolet radiation. The tholins form a hazy “molecular rain” that drifts on to the surface, giving Pluto its distinctive burnt color along its craters, mountains and cliffs.Researchers hypothesize that the tholins may actually ride the nitrogen ice flows beneath them, or along the dwarf planet’s winds.Nasa also released a new video describing the possible ice volcanos, also called cryovolcanos, believed to exist around the planet. Cryovolcanos spew frozen, volatile chemicals, such as ammonia and methane, rather than the ash and lava that erupts from volcanos on Earth.The rippled slopes of the 100-mile-wide Wright Mons, for instance, suggest the flow of melting, volatile chemicals from the mouth of the mountain, a depression estimated to be 35 miles wide. New Horizons did not capture images of eruptions, but cryovolcanos if confirmed would provide clues to how Pluto formed.New Horizons successfully flew by Pluto in July 2015, and has only transmitted a fraction of the total data it recorded; scientists expect a full download sometime this summer. The spacecraft is now heading off past the edge of the solar system, into a zone called the Kuiper belt, and should reach its next destination, a body called 2014MU69, in 2019.
</description>
<tags>
	pluto,space,nasa,science
</tags>