<seedurl>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us
</seedurl>
<url>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2016/jan/09/new-york-police-officer-shot
</url>
<title>
	New York police officer shot in ankle after responding to large fight
</title>
<description>
	Police exchanged gunfire with a suspect involved in early Saturday morning shootout and five people were hospitalized with stab woundsAuthorities said a New York City police officer was shot after exchanging gunfire with a suspect involved in a large fight, early on Saturday morning. Related: Philadelphia police identifies man who shot officer 'in name of Islam' Police commissioner William Bratton said the 25-year-old officer, Sherrod Stuart, was wounded on the fourth anniversary of his starting work with the department. Stuart was hospitalized with injuries that were not considered life-threatening, Bratton said.A 19-year-old suspect, Christopher Rice, was in serious condition at the same hospital, the commissioner said.Stuart and other officers were responding to a street fight that involved the use of guns, bats and knives and which broke out after a large party in the Bronx at around 2am, according to Bratton.Stuart was struck in the right foot during an exchange of gunfire with Rice, Bratton said. Stuart returned fire, striking Rice four times, according to Bratton.Five people were treated at hospitals for stab wounds, Bratton said, and four guns were recovered from the area.Bratton said Rice had five prior arrests – including one on Friday on a charge of fare beating. He said Rice was released from court at 11pm, three hours before the shooting.Bratton, who joined Mayor Bill de Blasio at a news conference at Lincoln Hospital after both men visited the wounded officer, said Stuart was the son of an NYPD detective who is currently on active duty with the US army.De Blasio called Stuart “an impressive young man who went into this very dangerous situation and handled himself so well”.Stuart was shot a day after a Philadelphia police officer was ambushed by a suspect and shot three times.Philadelphia officer Jesse Hartnett was in stable condition on Saturday. Police said a man confessed to shooting Hartnett and told investigators he had pledged his allegiance to the Islamic State group.
</description>
<tags>
	nypd,us news,new york
</tags>