<seedurl>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us
</seedurl>
<url>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2016/jan/09/zaevion-dobson-obama-gun-control-teen-killed
</url>
<title>
	In honoring Zaevion Dobson, will his death aid Obama's push for gun control?
</title>
<description>
	‘It’s like a big piece of your life is missing,’ a friend said of the slain teen whose bravery and death have become interwoven with the problem of gun violenceZaevion Dobson’s number 24 now lives in Knoxville infamy.It was emblazoned across the electronic signage out front of the city’s Fulton high school, it’s been reproduced on hundreds of T-shirts honoring the slain teen’s memory, and it lives in the hearts of those who knew 15-year-old Zaevion, many who called him simply, “Zae”.“It’s like a big piece of your life is missing – it’s just really dull and numb here,” said Fulton senior Jarien Green, a friend and team-mate of the teen whose bravery and tragic death has become interwoven this week with America’s long, winding reckoning with the problem of gun violence.Zaevion was killed by gunfire in Tennessee, eight days before Christmas when multiple shooters “randomly fired multiple times into a crowd”, according to Knoxville police. The teen dived on top of three girls when the incident began, using his body to protect them. All three survived the incident without injury, but Zaevion died at the scene.Faith Gordon, one of the girls Zaevion protected from the shots, said: “Once it was over I told Zaevion ‘get up’, and I was pulling him up by his hair, and I saw that he had gotten shot in the head.”Since that night, Zaevion’s memory has been embraced both by the Knoxville community that loved him and this week by Barack Obama as an example of the type of unnecessary violence that demands government action on gun control. Speaking from the East Room of the White House on Tuesday, the president’s tearful call for good people to feel the “fierce urgency of now” on guns came to a heart-rending end when he talked about the heroism of Zaevion. “He wasn’t in the wrong place at the wrong time. He hadn’t made a bad decision. He was exactly where any other kid would be. Your kid. My kids. And then gunmen started firing. And Zaevion – who was in high school, hadn’t even gotten started in life – dove on top of three girls to shield them from the bullets. And he was shot in the head. And the girls were spared. He gave his life to save theirs – an act of heroism a lot bigger than anything we should ever expect from a 15-year-old. ‘Greater love hath no man than this that a man lay down his life for his friends.’ We are not asked to do what Zaevion Dobson did. We’re not asked to have shoulders that big; a heart that strong; reactions that quick. I’m not asking people to have that same level of courage, or sacrifice, or love. But if we love our kids and care about their prospects, and if we love this country and care about its future, then we can find the courage to vote. We can find the courage to get mobilized and organized. We can find the courage to cut through all the noise and do what a sensible country would do. That’s what we’re doing today. And tomorrow, we should do more. And we should do more the day after that. And if we do, we’ll leave behind a nation that’s stronger than the one we inherited and worthy of the sacrifice of a young man like Zaevion.The speech outlined a series of executive actions Obama’s administration was taking, including expanded background checks and requiring universal licensing for gun sellers. Obama also called on Congress to act by providing increased funding for mental healthcare. “It almost gave me peace,” Green said of hearing the president talk about his friend. “A figure like Obama has hundreds of millions of things to worry about on a day-to-day basis. For him to take time out of his day to worry about my brother, my friend, my team-mate – it warmed my heart.” “Just hearing him recognize my son – and he called his name more than once – that really made my heart feel glad,” Dobson’s mother Zenobia told the Knoxville News-Sentinel. “It’s time for a change, and it took someone like my son to stand up on the frontline, to be courageous.”Green said it’s fitting that so far, Zaevion’s memorialization has been of him as a football player, number 24 for the Fulton Falcons. Zaevion loved the game. One of Zaevion’s dreams, one now cut tragically short, was to play college football and then return to Fulton high as a coach.Under “employer” his Facebook profile boasts “NFL”. It may have been wishful thinking, but he prepared like a pro. One of only a few sophomores who played on the varsity team, Zaevion took game film home to watch and improve – be ready for the next opponent.“He was a guy that was always prepared. I thought about that when I heard what happened,” said Fulton’s football head coach, Rob Black. “I thought, ‘that’s him!’ He was prepared to do whatever. He prepared himself on the football field and he prepared himself in life. That’s one of the things that makes him such a special kid.”Although police believe the shots that killed Zaevion were random, they also suspect that the shooting, one in a related string of three that evening, was gang-related. One of the suspected gunmen, Brandon Perry, died later that night in a car accident. Another, 20-year-old Christopher Bassett, is in custody.Green said the best way to move forward from Zaevion’s loss is to simply “keep pushing”.“That’s what he was doing and that’s what he would want us to do,” Green said. “So let’s just honor him and keep striving to be better each day, because we don’t know if we’ll even have the next day.”
</description>
<tags>
	us gun control,barack obama,gun crime,us news,tennessee
</tags>