<seedurl>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us
</seedurl>
<url>
	http://www.theguardian.com/books/2016/jan/08/petition-terry-pratchett-element-octarine-discworld-colour-of-magic
</url>
<title>
	Petition launched to name new element after Terry Pratchett's colour of magic
</title>
<description>
	Scientist’s proposal of ‘Octarine’, the Discworld shade visible only to wizards and cats, for newly discovered element 117 gains 12,000 signatures in two daysA petition to name one of the new elements added to the periodic table “octarine”, in honour of the late Terry Pratchett’s colour of magic, has garnered more than 12,000 signatures in less than two days.The International Union of Pure and Applied Chemistry (IUPAC) announced the verification of the discoveries of four new chemical elements earlier this week. Currently known as elements 113, 115, 117 and 118, they will be officially named by the teams that discovered them in the months to come, but chemist Dr Kat Day, who blogs at the Chronicle Flask, has put in an early bid for element 117 to be named octarine. Related: Neil Gaiman: ‘Terry Pratchett isn’t jolly. He’s angry’ “This petition is to name element 117, recently confirmed by the International Union of Pure and Applied Chemistry, as ‘Octarine’, with the proposed symbol Oc (pronounced ‘ook’), in honour of the late Terry Pratchett and his Discworld series of books,” she writes in a petition to the scientists who discovered the element. At the time of writing, two days after it was launched, the bid has already garnered 12,851 signatories – as well as the support of the late author’s Twitter feed, @terryandrob, which is now run by his assistant, Rob Wilkins. “Name element 117 Octarine? If you think that’s a good idea – and we do – please sign the petition here,” @terryandrob tweeted.Pratchett, who died in March 2015, writes in his first Discworld novel, The Colour of Magic, that octarine is “the King Colour, of which all the lesser colours are merely partial and wishy-washy reflections. It was octarine, the colour of magic. It was alive and glowing and vibrant and it was the undisputed pigment of the imagination, because wherever it appeared it was a sign that mere matter was a servant of the powers of the magical mind. It was enchantment itself. But Rincewind always thought it looked a sort of greenish-purple.” Day’s proposal for the symbol to be pronounced “ook” is a tribute to Pratchett’s Librarian at the Unseen University. She announced the launch of the petition on her blog with another quote from Pratchett: “It is well known that a vital ingredient of success is not knowing that what you’re attempting can’t be done.”“Octarine, in the Discworld books, is known as ‘the colour of magic’, which forms the title of Pratchett’s first ever Discworld book,” the petition says. “According to Disc mythology, octarine is visible only to wizards and cats, and is generally described as a sort of greenish-yellow purple colour, which seems perfect for what will probably be the final halogen in the periodic table. Octarine is also a particularly pleasing choice because not only would it honour a world-famous and much-loved author, but it also has an ‘ine’ ending, consistent with the other elements in group 17.”“Octarine is being counted as ‘a mythological concept’ under IUPAC rules, which state that elements must be named after ‘a mythological concept or character; a mineral, or similar substance; a place or geographical region; a property of the element; or a scientist’. The Discworld stories are certainly stories about gods and heroes, and 70m books surely count for something.” Day, who has a PhD in chemistry and has taught the subject for more than a decade, adds on her blog: “OK, they’re not quite as old as the Greek myths, but they will be one day, right? Time is relative and all that.”She urged her followers to sign, speculating that the Russian and American scientists at the Joint Institute for Nuclear Research in Dubna, Moscow, and Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory in California who discovered elements 115, 117 and 118 could be Discworld fans.“You never know,” she wrote. “If nothing else I’m absolutely certain that Sir Terry, the author of the Science of the Discworld series of books, would have a little chuckle at the idea.” Related: Periodic table's seventh row finally filled as four new elements are added Those signing up to the petition also appeared delighted with the suggestion. “I’ve taught high-school chemistry for 37 years, and been a devoted Pratchett fan for over 25,” wrote one. “Considering Sir Terry’s writing background as a reporter covering the nuclear energy industry, his interest in science and the degree to which he advanced scientific curiosity in of mind of the general public, I can think of nobody more deserving of this honour.”“As a graduate chemist and a Pratchett fan for more than 25 years, how can I not sign!” said another. “This is a very fitting tribute to a terrific man who did much to further people’s interest in science.”Larry Finlay, managing director at Pratchett’s publishers Transworld agreed, saying he thought “nothing that would have pleased Terry more.” “Having element 117 named Octarine in his honour would have tickled him pink,” said Finlay, “or should that be a greenish-yellow purple?”
</description>
<tags>
	terry pratchett,fantasy,fiction,books,culture,science,periodic table,chemistry
</tags>