<seedurl>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us
</seedurl>
<url>
	http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2016/jan/08/nypd-spied-muslim-americans-will-court-settlement-bring-change
</url>
<title>
	The NYPD spied on Muslim Americans. Will a court settlement change anything?
</title>
<description>
	The effects of surveillance on New York Muslim communities have been devastating – but this settlement can help prevent more harmful policingIn the current moment of mounting anti-Muslim sentiment nationwide and misguided calls from some politicians for a security crackdown on Muslims, there is some welcome news: the New York police department has agreed to reforms that prohibit the discriminatory surveillance of Muslim communities.Five years ago, news broke that the NYPD was engaged in an expansive domestic spying operation targeting American Muslim communities for surveillance, mapping and infiltration. Two lawsuits were filed in the New York federal courts in response to these practices and in defense New York City Muslims’ – and all minority communities’ – right to equal treatment and religious freedom.On Thursday, both lawsuits were settled. If approved by the courts, the settlement would reinforce existing safeguards on surveillance of political and religious activities, create new ones and embed civilian oversight within the NYPD.  Related: NYPD settles lawsuits over surveillance of Muslims and agrees to reforms We hope the principles reflected in the settlement will not just ensure bias-free and effective policing by the NYPD, but will also serve as guideposts in the current security and civil liberties debates. To our clients and their communities, the news stories five years ago – which culminated in a Pulitzer prize for the Associated Press – were not a revelation, but confirmation of what they had known or suspected for years. As detailed in our lawsuit and in a report titled, Mapping Muslims, the effects of surveillance on New York Muslim communities have been devastating. Imams are reluctant to counsel congregants, fearing they may be informants. Community members’ ties to local police precincts have deteriorated due to distrust and fear that reporting to police on matters of daily concern, like street crime or domestic violence, would result in surveillance. Parents tell their children not to “dress too Muslim” or be active in Muslim student associations to avoid police monitoring. Fear deters people from discussing current events.Bias-based policing legitimizes religious discrimination. It can pave the way to copy-cat approaches by other agencies and set the stage for hate crimes nationwide. Predictably, discrimination against one minority community spreads to others, and leaked documents and reports confirm NYPD spying on progressive and anti-war groups as well as the Black Lives Matter movement. For all these reasons, we hope the settlement announced this week pulls our city and its police department out of a downward spiral by reaffirming core values and principles, ones just as necessary to a local police force as they are to a rational debate on civil rights and liberties nationally. Both New York City and the nation must respond to the threat of violence – whatever its source – without tearing apart the fabric of our nation by violating the principles it proclaims. One such principle is equal protection, a bulwark against biased policing as well as any national proposal to surveil, detain, or ban Muslims. As part of the settlement, the NYPD explicitly recognizes the right to be free from investigations in which race, religion or ethnicity is a substantial or motivating factor. Another core principle is the need for safeguards on the considerable power wielded by the police in our country. The settlement would only allow intrusive investigations by the NYPD when they are based on allegations of unlawful activity that are articulable and factual, meaning that mere hunches are not enough. Investigations would also be subject to presumptive time limits and could not be prolonged indefinitely. And, importantly to communities that live in fear of monitoring and infiltration, undercovers and informants would only be deployed in the absence of less intrusive alternatives. These safeguards are especially important at a time of rising Islamophobia. Experts and police officials have found that Muslims are no more prone to terrorism than any other group and that the greatest threat of political violence in this country comes not from Muslims but from rightwing militants. The authorities don’t map where white people live or systematically send informants to majority white communities to ferret out potential right wing extremists or mass shooters, nor should they. Simply put, prejudice is not police work, and crime cannot be prevented by the mass stereotyping of entire communities. It’s both wrong and wastes resources that should be devoted to investigating actual wrongdoing.Finally, the settlement would install a critically important check within the NYPD. A civilian representative would be appointed by the mayor and empowered to ensure all safeguards are followed in police investigations directed at political and religious activities. Together with the recently created the office of the NYPD inspector general, the civilian representative would bring external oversight and rights enforcement to the NYPD. Perhaps needless to say, the settlement is no panacea, but according to the lead plaintiff in our case, Imam Hamid Raza, it is “important progress”.It is a platform upon which to build further reform and advance shared goals of a more just society and policing. The settlement will help ensure policing in New York City does not have a misplaced focus on religion, ideology, and race and directs attention and resources towards actual criminal conduct. A similar path nationally may be a long one, but we hope the rest of the country follows.
</description>
<tags>
	nypd,surveillance
</tags>