<seedurl>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us
</seedurl>
<url>
	http://www.theguardian.com/books/2016/jan/08/why-books-like-fifty-shades-of-grey-are-worthy-of-study
</url>
<title>
	Why books like Fifty Shades of Grey are worthy of study
</title>
<description>
	Lawmakers are calling for Missouri academic Melissa Click to be fired – in part because she conducts research on romance novels, and the hypocrisy is revealingPoliticians hate romance. In Missouri, over 100 state legislators have called for assistant professor of journalism Melissa Click to be fired. The main cause of complaint stems from a video showing Click demanding that a student journalist stop photographing a protest at the University of Missouri. There’s some jostling and shoving, which the legislators characterise as “inappropriate and criminal actions”. They say it’s an assault on free speech.And then to show how much they care about free speech, the legislators declare, “Our constituents have expressed outrage at the fact she is using taxpayer dollars to conduct research on Fifty Shades of Grey, Lady Gaga and Twilight.” Free speech means only researching things that the government approves, apparently.The hypocrisy is more or less expected; just about everyone is more enthusiastic about free speech for folks they agree with than for folks they don’t. The effort to leverage Fifty Shades of Grey for political point scoring has precedent, though. This isn’t the first time legislators have ginned up outrage over the scholarly study of romance. In 2013 and 2014, conservative politicians and media raised a stink about NEH funding of the Popular Romance Project. “Federal government has spent nearly $1m on romance,” a Yahoo headline blared. Funding for romance scholarship was presented as wasteful, frivolous, and unnecessary – a clear example of government overreach and inefficiency. The furore did in fact affect NEH funding, and the Popular Romance Project had to scale back their website – though with other funding they went on to hold a successful conference and help fund the critically lauded documentary Love Between the Covers.Why is romance such an easy target for politicians? Eric Selinger, a professor of English at DePaul University, and the academic adviser to the Popular Romance Project, pointed out that conservative politicians have been increasingly sceptical of funding for the humanities as a whole. Within the humanities, popular culture is seen as especially unimportant – and then: “Within popular culture, popular romance is a particularly tempting target because it has to do with women, it has to do with sex. It’s long been seen as a fairly trivial cultural enterprise.”Anything associated with women’s pleasures, aesthetic or sexual, has long generated anxiety and scandalous murmurs. Hawthorne famously characterised female authors as “damn mobs of scribbling women” while Jane Austen declared of (female romance) novelists: “Although our productions have afforded more extensive and unaffected pleasure than those of any other literary corporation in the world, no species of composition has been so much decried.” In last year’s Dangerous Books for Girls, romance novelist Maya Rodale argues that historically, romance has made people nervous because it encouraged women’s pleasure – not least sexual pleasure.” There were genuine concerns that women would develop unrealistic expectations about their lives by reading fiction,” she writes. She also points out: “Romantic fiction relentlessly declares that women are worthy and their interests are valid and it is worth it for them to pursue their own happiness.” Bobbi Dumas made similar points in a 2012 essay at NPR: “In romance, we are the creators, the intended audience and the receptive consumer, showing our appreciation through astronomical sales. Female writers writing for female readers about traditionally female interests.”Fifty Shades, Twilight and for that matter Lady Gaga are not just trivial – they’re dangerous because they’re trivial. Women’s interests, and women’s happiness, aren’t worthy of study, in part because if you decide they are worthy of study, then women, happiness and sex, all become important. And then goodness knows what will happen.Fifty Shades of Grey is important, of course, at least if you think that massively popular books are important. The romance genre as a whole generated $1.4bn in sales in 2013, close to twice as much as the next biggest genre, crime and mystery. Aaron Kashtan, a visiting assistant professor of English at Miami University in Ohio who does research on comics, told me that “the primary reason to study pop culture is because it both reflects and shapes what people think.” Romance, including work like Fifty Shades and Twilight, are hugely popular – and so do a lot of shaping and reflecting, for better or worse.In fact, the legislative antipathy to romance is an acknowledgement of its high cultural profile – and is therefore a kind of backhanded validation of the genre. Eric Selinger pointed out that politicians used romance as an example of government waste because any discussion of romance novels is sexy and arresting; it generates headlines. Similarly, the Missouri legislators glommed on to Click’s research interests as a way to discredit her because Fifty Shades and Twilight resonate; people care about them. Their very mention provokes outrage, because they’re powerful symbols of sex, of frivolity, and of the dangerous, sinister forces sapping American strength and undermining our values.Politicians love to hate romance precisely because they know Fifty Shades is something people care about. If romance matters enough to be an object of hatred and political manipulation, therefore, it seems like it should matter enough to be an object of study as well.
</description>
<tags>
	fifty shades of grey,twilight,romance,lady gaga,books,culture,fiction
</tags>