<seedurl>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us
</seedurl>
<url>
	http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2016/jan/09/mexico-caught-el-chapo-again-but-hell-likely-live-to-escape-another-day
</url>
<title>
	Mexico caught El Chapo, again. But he'll likely live to escape another day
</title>
<description>
	Cartel boss Joaquín Guzmán knows Mexican corruption better than anyone, because he lives or dies – escapes or remains imprisoned – by itThough President Enrique Peña Nieto has announced “Mission accomplished” following news of Joaquín “El Chapo” Guzmán’s recapture Friday, I’m actually very excited for the drug cartel kingpin’s next escape.As the trajectory goes, we can expect it to be even more fabulous than his last, more intricately planned and executed than even the tunnel get-away in which Guzmán burrowed his way out of maximum security prison – Shawshank Redemption style – through his jail cell’s shower and rode a motor bike through a lighted underground tunnel to freedom a mile away.In the spirit of radical honesty I’ll say this: that was awesome. Almost a national day of pride for Mexican people everywhere because the story was so ridiculous, so far-fetched (but somehow real), that it could have only happened in Mexico, facilitated by Mexican corruption. It was both laughably tragic and deliciously schadenfreude. Guzmán became the populist hero who could clown the party in power harder than anyone could clown them while using their own weapon against them, no less: the refined art of Mexican corruption.Mexican corruption has created Chapo Guzmán, our Mexican James Bond, Robin Hood, Jesus Malverde and Bogeyman all rolled into one. And like any great legend, he’ll continue to exist (despite or in spite of Peña Nieto’s wishes) because both Mexicans and Americans need him to exist. Sure, America needs its drugs. But more than that, America needs its drug war, of which El Chapo is the face and this new era of hyper-rampant Mexican corruption symptom. Chapo knows Mexican corruption better than anyone, because he lives or dies by it. He escapes or doesn’t escape by it.The tradition of Mexican corruption is how Guzmán made his first escape from the notorious Puente Grande prison in January of 2001 despite having been assigned at least two prison guards in addition to extra surveillance cameras on him at all times. It has been speculated that Guzmán bribed prison guards to dismantle surveillance cameras in order to better smuggle him outside of the prison in a laundry cart.From there, he rode a truck to an undisclosed location to continue operating his massive Sinaloa Cartel empire, arguably the most powerful cartel—in both capital and fire power – in all of Mexico. It’s evident, too, that corruption facilitated Guzmán’s second escape from the Altiplano high-security prison outside of Mexico City, in which the prison’s CCTV shows guards unresponsive to the racket accompanying the massive construction project that would facilitate Guzmán’s departure only months after his capture in February 2014. In the meanwhile, Peña Nieto will likely try to sell Chapo Guzmán’s latest capture as a win for the administration. Peña Nieto will try to show to the world that his administration can, and will be, tough on crime (never mind the Grupo Higa scandal, in which the president was cleared of charges that he improperly purchased property from public contractors, or the “historical truth” – the administration’s shifting story – concerning the missing Ayotzinapa students). He’ll probably talk about the systematic corruption in Mexico and draw a line between the Mexican government and criminals themselves. He’ll even likely try to proclaim some vague victory over cartel influence in Mexico. But let’s remember how El Chapo escapes time after time: the collusion of organized crime with public officials. As security analyst Jorge Kawas told the Guardian: “Some powerful people in the (Mexican) elite should be worried if El Chapo decides to spill the beans.” The gears will turn. Systematic corruption will continue. And Chapo will escape once again. Only this time, I hope there will be an airplane involved.
</description>
<tags>
	mexico,americas,drugs trade
</tags>