<seedurl>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us
</seedurl>
<url>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2016/jan/09/police-investigate-philadelphia-shooting-suspect-computers-finances-travel-history-edward-archer
</url>
<title>
	Police investigate Philadelphia shooting suspect's computers and finances
</title>
<description>
	The travel history, computers and finances of the man suspected of shooting a Philadelphia police officer on Thursday have been swept into an FBI investigation into the attack, though officials have downplayed the suspect’s alleged oath to terrorists. Related: Philadelphia police identifies man who shot officer 'in name of Islam' Police said Edward Archer, 33, had pledged allegiance to the Islamic State, though there is no proof he has any affiliation with members of the terrorist group. Archer travelled to Saudi Arabia for a pilgrimage to Mecca in 2011, and went to Egypt for several months in 2012, FBI spokesman Eric Ruona told the Guardian on Saturday. Ruona said that the federal agency was looking into those trips as well as Archer’s finances and electronic computer records to create “the fullest picture”.There is no indication that Archer had any affiliation to known terrorists, according to officials. “We don’t have anything about that now but that’s something we’re looking at and trying to figure out,” Ruona said.Archer told investigators that police-enforced laws counter the teachings of the Qur’an, officials said on Friday.“We will see where the investigation leads us,” Philadelphia’s police commissioner, Richard Ross, who was sworn in this week, said on Friday.Officials and Archer’s family have disputed claims that the attack was religiously motivated, and investigators have so far declined to ascribe a specific motive to the shooting.Archer’s mother, Valerie Holliday, told the Philadelphia Inquirer on Friday that her son had been hearing voices and their family had been encouraging him to seek medical help.FBI terrorism taskforce agents searched Holliday’s home on Friday and left with a cardboard box and evidence bags.Philadelphia’s mayor, Jim Kenney, who also took office this week, commended the police for their response to the shooting.“Last night’s shooting had nothing to do with any faith,” Kenney tweeted on Friday. “It was a violent assault by a criminal. I urge all Philadelphians to stand together.”At about 11.40pm on Thursday, Archer approached Jesse Hartnett’s patrol car in the middle of a street and opened fire. He fired at least 13 shots as he neared the car, and eventually leaned into the vehicle and discharged another round.He then ran from the scene. Hartnett, who was shot three times, exited his vehicle and pursued Archer, shooting him once in the buttocks, police said. A group of nearby police officers captured Archer after hearing Hartnett report the shooting on police radio.Ross said that a 9mm pistol was recovered at the scene. The weapon was stolen from an officer’s home in October 2013, according to police. It is unclear how Archer obtained it. Archer pleaded guilty to firearms and assault charges in March 2014. He was scheduled to be sentenced in a traffic and forgery case on Monday.Halliday said her son had been a practicing Muslim for some time and that she did not know where he got the gun. “I’m still hoping they have the wrong child,” she told the Inquirer.Hartnett, a four-year veteran of the force, was seriously wounded in the shooting and is recovering in the hospital. He is in stable condition, which Ross called “absolutely amazing”.“It’s nothing short of miraculous and we’re thankful for that,” Ross said.Kenney, who praised Hartnett’s bravery, said the shooting was indicative of the gun violence problem. Two-hundred and eighty people were murdered in Philadelphia in 2015, a three-year high but still less than the six years 2007-2012, when more than 300 people were killed in the city on average. “There are too many guns on our streets,” Kenney said.
</description>
<tags>
	philadelphia,us news,pennsylvania,gun crime,us policing
</tags>