<seedurl>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us
</seedurl>
<url>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2016/jan/08/bill-clinton-hillary-campaign-trail-iowa-donald-trump
</url>
<title>
	Bill Clinton avoids taking Donald Trump's bait as he campaigns for Hillary
</title>
<description>
	On the campaign trail the former president declined to discuss Trump, who released a video criticizing Hillary Clinton as a defender of women’s rightsWhile political rivals, pundits and journalists remain obsessed with Donald Trump, granting him publicity that money can’t buy, one man spent the week studiously avoiding any mention of him.Bill Clinton did not use the “T” word during his stump speeches in Iowa and New Hampshire as he entered the campaign fray on behalf of his wife, Hillary. This was despite Trump goading him with characteristically blunt references to past sexual indiscretions.So far at least, the former president has not taken the bait, seeking instead to rise above the trading of insults that can fuel the news cycle. There were just shy of 800 attendees at both of Clinton’s events in New Hampshire this week, roughly the same as the crowd size Hillary drew while campaigning in the state a day earlier. Those expecting a verbal prize fight with Trump were disappointed.But when Clinton moved on to Iowa, shaking hands, posing for selfies and sampling a green fruit and vegetable smoothie, a TV journalist blocked his path and attempted to force the issue. Asked if he could be a liability to Hillary’s campaign as Trump revives old scandals, he replied: “I don’t have a response. If he wins the Republican nomination, we’ll have plenty of time to talk about it if Hillary wins.”He added: “I don’t want to be involved in their politics or do anything except trying to help Hillary.” Trump has declared Clinton’s past troubles fair game. On Thursday he released a video that juxtaposed arguably Hillary’s finest hour as first lady – a 1995 speech in Beijing where she declared “human rights are women’s rights and women’s rights are human rights” – with photos of Clinton with Monica Lewinsky (the White House intern with whom he had an extramarital affair), a newspaper front page branding Clinton “Liar, liar”, and the sex scandal-plagued Anthony Weiner – husband of her trusted aide Huma Abedin. Finally, the video ended on an image of Hillary Clinton with Bill Cosby, and a caption reading: “True defender of women’s rights.”Hillary tweeted later that day: “It’s important to stand up to bullies wherever they are.”Sexual allegations against Bill Clinton from the late 1970s were revived in the media from a self-declared Trump supporter. Last month, Hillary was challenged at a town hall meeting in New Hampshire by a woman who asked her directly about three women who have made historic allegations about her husband.Trump’s efforts to challenge Hillary Clinton’s record on women’s rights comes as she enters this weekend seeking to harness the support of young women, by enlisting Lena Dunham, creator of the series Girls, on the campaign trail in Iowa. Polls have shown that Clinton’s rival, the Vermont senator Bernie Sanders, has consistently polled higher with young voters.Trump is not alone in seeking to conflate Hillary with her husband’s record as president. After it emerged that North Korea had conducted a nuclear test this week, Republican candidate Ted Cruz told reporters: “It’s worth remembering North Korea has a nuclear weapon today because of the Clinton administration. The Clinton administration led the world in relaxing sanctions against North Korea. They used the billions of dollars that flowed into North Korea to develop nuclear weapons. Now we’re facing a megalomaniacal maniac who may potentially have a hydrogen bomb.”Hammering the Clintons plays well with the Republican base, although there is little evidence over time that highlighting the former president’s infidelity hurts Hillary at the polls. Bill Clinton is expected to be a more visible presence in the lead-up to the 1 February caucuses in Iowa and 9 February New Hampshire primary. Next week the couple’s daughter, Chelsea, will be deployed in New Hampshire.For his part, Clinton may be anxious to avoid the experience of 2008 when his attacks on Barack Obama, including his description of Obama’s stance on the Iraq war as a “fairytale”, appeared to backfire. “I don’t fit any more,” he said in Nashua, New Hampshire, this week. “First of all, I’m a happy grandfather. I’m not mad at anybody.”Shaun Bowler, professor of political science at the University of California Riverside, suggested that the former president’s refusal to fight Trump on his own turf is probably wise. “In terms of Trump, my sense is that at this stage in the campaign he is defining himself and not being defined by others,” he said. “To date the attempts by others to paint him – as a loose cannon for example – do not seem to have made much of an impression on him or his supporters.“In that context, at the present time, it doesn’t seem as if there is much that Bill Clinton can say or do to change that. Also, I’m not sure it is Bill Clinton’s role to engage with Trump. At this point it seems more about introducing him to the electorate via the campaign so that – post-convention – people are familiar with him. Whatever his accomplishments and achievements in the past, Bill Clinton’s current job is to stand by his spouse.”
</description>
<tags>
	bill clinton,hillary clinton,donald trump,us elections 2016,iowa,new hampshire,us politics,lena dunham,us news
</tags>