<seedurl>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us
</seedurl>
<url>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2016/jan/09/powerball-drawing-record-jackpot-announcement
</url>
<title>
	$800m Powerball drawing: lottery ticket holders await fates as jackpot swells
</title>
<description>
	Lottery officials expect winning numbers to be announced this weekend but if there are no matches the next drawing could rise to $1.3bnThe Powerball jackpot increased to $900m on Saturday, just hours before the drawing. Related: Record $800m Powerball jackpot will be a major win for the IRS The drawing was due to be held at 10.59pm ET. Lottery officials said a winner would have choose between being paid $900m through annual payments over 29 years or a $558m lump-sum cash payout.Sales for the lottery game have skyrocketed since Wednesday, when no one won an estimated $500m jackpot. Officials said that if no one won on Saturday, the next jackpot would be $1.3bn.For this weekend’s record drawing, about 65% of the possible number combinations will have been bought, officials with the Multi-State Lottery Association, which runs the Powerball game, said on Friday. That percentage could rise if the jackpot estimate was increased, they said – but even lottery officials said they did not know what to expect.“You can throw out the logic. You can throw out the statistics,” said Gary Grief, executive director of the Texas Lottery. “We’ve never seen jackpots like this. It’s a new experience for all of us.”Since 4 November, the Powerball jackpot has grown from its $40m starting point. Grief is more certain what will happen if no one matches the numbers on five white balls and the one red Powerball this time.“It will definitely go past $1bn if we roll past this Saturday,” he said.This kind of huge jackpot was just what lottery officials hoped for last fall when they changed the odds of matching all the Powerball numbers, from about one in 175 million to one in 292.2 million. By making it harder to win a jackpot, the tougher odds made the ever-larger prizes inevitable.The bigger prizes draw more players, who in turn make the jackpots even bigger.So many people were buying Powerball tickets in Iowa that lottery spokeswoman Mary Neubauer said some stores were running out of paper for tickets, leaving lottery workers scrambling to resupply the outlets.The odds are a matter of statistics and probability, but they are facts that most players may not completely understand, said Ron Wasserstein, executive director of the Alexandria, Virginia-based American Statistical Association.“Once you get numbers that size, it’s hard for people to wrap their minds around them,” Wasserstein said.It’s not like players ever had a great shot at winning a jackpot, but by lengthening the odds, he said, “you take odds that were really, really small before, and now they’re nearly twice as small as they were before.”Players in Lincoln, Nebraska, said they did not expect to win, but most noted that eventually someone will take home all that money.Gary Diaz of Lincoln said he had bought one or two Powerball tickets every week since a group of his co-workers won a lottery jackpot in 2004.“Ever since then, I go, ‘Hell, if it happened once, it’s gotta happen again,’” Diaz said. “It’s all by chance.”Bashir Rahman, a chef from Moscow, Idaho, who was traveling through Nebraska, said he decided to buy a couple of tickets at a Casey’s gas station in Lincoln, but he realizes it’s a long, long shot.“You buy more than two, you’re just stupid,” he said.Wasserstein said he understands why so many people buy Powerball tickets, calling it a small price for a chance to dream of immense riches. But Wasserstein said he and his colleagues know too well the nearly impossible odds to plunk down even $2 for a ticket.“I can assure you,” he said, “there is no office pool for the lottery at the American Statistical Association.”
</description>
<tags>
	us news
</tags>