<seedurl>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us
</seedurl>
<url>
	http://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/jan/09/germany-sex-attacks-cologne-immigration
</url>
<title>
	Germany after the sex attacks: fences are going up and the mood is ugly
</title>
<description>
	‘Cologne’ has become a byword for all the fears, prejudices and – let’s face it – real problems associated with mass immigrationWomen are sniggered at, insulted, and find men’s hands down their tops and between their legs. Dark corners are dangerous; girls who are drunk and alone are chased and raped. Security and police are nowhere to be seen. Welcome to Oktoberfest, Munich’s annual beer saturnalia. The worst, say barmaids, are Brits and Italians.Cut to New Year’s Eve in Cologne. Crowds of people, mostly young men in various stages of inebriation, gather on the square between the cathedral and the station to let off fireworks and let themselves go. The crowd, about 1,000 strong, is watched by around 200 police, worried about youths throwing fireworks at each other.But something more sinister is going on. Women and girls are surrounded, poked and jeered at as “whores” and “cunts”; their blouses are ripped and their underwear torn off. “I had mens’ hands on every body opening,” a distraught girl told the police. More than 100 women file sexual molestation charges against men “of north African or Arab origin”. Yet the station is not cleared, few arrests are made and, the next morning, the police report a “quiet night”. It takes almost four days for Germany to wake up to what happened. Related: Cologne protests over sex attacks: ‘I am full of sorrow for Germany’ Since then, the country has been talking about little else. North Korea’s H-bomb? The Charlie Hebdo anniversary? Europe’s descent into petty nationalism? Forget it. “Cologne” has become a byword for all the fears, prejudices and – let’s face it – real problems associated with mass immigration. German railway stations were symbols of Willkommenskultur, with crowds welcoming refugees from Syria and elsewhere. Now a station has become a symbol for what some are calling Islamic “rape culture”.Questions remain. Who were the men? A leaked police report says many waved asylum papers – their only ID – in officers’ faces, then tore them up, saying they’d soon get new ones. One reportedly said: “You can’t touch me. I’m Syrian: Merkel wants me here.”Asylum workers deny that refugees were in the majority and say gangs of Moroccans and other north Africans control the pickpocketing around stations in Cologne, Hamburg and Stuttgart, where incidents of sexual harassment were also reported. Then there’s the police: 200 officers ought to be able to manage 1,000 mostly drunk men. Why didn’t they intervene? Why did they lie? Was it political correctness? Or a feeling that molesting women is part of a good night’s fun?Finally, the media: were journalists loth to admit that what populists rant about had actually happened? The truth is probably more innocuous. The police lacked leadership: Cologne’s chief of police has now been sacked. Journalists were still in post-holiday recovery mode. But that won’t stick with supporters of Pegida – “Patriotic Europeans Against the Islamisation of Europe” – or populist party Alternative für Deutschland. They regularly accuse the police and justice system of exaggerated political correctness, and the press of blindly supporting Merkel’s “population exchange” plan, covering up immigrants’ crimes and demonising those who dare talk about them. Related: Angela Merkel seeks tougher laws to deport migrants after Cologne sex attacks It didn’t help that Cologne’s mayor, Henriette Reker, who was the victim of a racist knife attack before her election last October, advised women to stay “at arm’s length” from strangers. This drew a rebuff by Merkel’s minister for the family, the elderly, women and youth. “It isn’t women who must change their behaviour,” Manuela Schwesig fumed, “but men.”Double standards abound. Writer Birgit Kelle, an ethnic German from Romania, condemned the “unacceptable image of women” brought into Germany by Muslims. Yet a few years ago she reacted to women’s protests against sexual harassment in the workplace with a bestselling book entitled: Then button up your Blouse! Most anti-immigration protesters also decry feminism, gender mainstreaming, sex education in schools and so on, but it’s no use pointing out these contradictions when emotions are running high. When someone brought up the Oktoberfest parallels, Muslim-haters started a Facebook campaign arguing that, with 5.9 million visitors over a week, “only” 20 women were raped last year, whereas now 1,000 immigrants had attacked more than 100 women in one night. Do the maths, they jeered.Cologne happened just as it seemed that Angela Merkel’s gamble of shaming the rest of Europe into accepting more refugees might be paying off. The immigration bureaucracy announced that it was now coping. Money and blandishments were offered to Turkey to stem the flow of refugees into Greece, and Merkel was tipped to play the modern-day Bismarck in the negotiations on Syria.The AfD is expected to do well in regional elections this year, but this would play into Merkel’s hands by forcing the other parties into coalitions with her weakened but still dominant CDU.After Cologne, however, the populists are on a roll, with the centre and the liberal left in disarray. Feminist magazine Emma wrote that it had been “flooded by calls for help” and that the “hundreds of thousands of mostly young men streaming into the country from cultures that despise women” could endanger 200 years of struggle for human rights and 40 years of gains for women’s equality.Pegida is marching in Cologne this weekend. Merkel, true to form, has bowed to populist pressure and talked about increasing the – already high and rising – number of deportations. Expect more hard talk and tough measures. It may not be enough to save her chancellorship.Elsewhere in the EU, the new nationalist government in Poland reacted gleefully to the Cologne catastrophe. This, they trumpeted, was why they would not bow to German pressure to accept more refugees. Governments in Hungary, Slovakia and the Czech Republic agreed. Fear of immigrants has already all but destroyed the Schengen passport-free zone and the elite liberal consensus that decries nationalism and racism as the roots of Europe’s past troubles.Fences are going up everywhere, including in people’s minds. The mood is ugly across the continent today. And it’s not likely get better soon.
</description>
<tags>
	germany,europe,world news,european union,migration
</tags>