<seedurl>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us
</seedurl>
<url>
	http://www.theguardian.com/stage/2016/jan/08/an-evening-with-groucho-marx-frank-ferrante-broadway-bath-pasadena-playhouse
</url>
<title>
	In Groucho's club: 30 years of playing a Marx brother
</title>
<description>
	Decades after his one-man show wowed Broadway and the West End, Frank Ferrante is returning to pay homage to the comedy legend who changed his lifeThey called him Groucho for a reason, but no one knows what it is. It could have been his sour disposition or a nod to Groucho the Monk, a comic book character. Then again, it might have been about the money pouch he wore around his neck bearing the same grumpy moniker. But one thing is certain about Julius Henry Marx, Minnie’s third son after Chico and Harpo, with Gummo and Zeppo waiting in the wings: he didn’t suffer fools gladly.“Are you making any more Marx Brothers movies?” he was asked at one of his final appearances before his death at the age of 86 in 1977. “No,” he responded, “I’m answering stupid questions.” Frank Ferrante remembers that day at the Ambassador Hotel in Los Angeles. Only 13 at the time, he sat at the feet of one of his idols only to find the eyes that used to sparkle with wit were now watery and vague. When the Q&A was over, he followed Groucho and his handlers to a limo and watched them drive away. At the time, he couldn’t imagine the comedian would have such a profound impact on his life. Ferrante has been playing him in one form or another since he first mounted his one-man show, An Evening With Groucho, as part of his USC thesis in 1985. This weekend, he brings his act to the Pasadena Playhouse ahead of tour dates in the US and a one-night stand in Bath as part of a Marx Brothers festival in April. It will be his first performance in the UK since the play’s triple Olivier-nominated run in 1987. For a student production, that USC show drew an impressive list of Groucho confidants courtesy of producer and Marx Brothers aficionado Bob Weide (producer of Curb Your Enthusiasm). Included were Arthur and Miriam Marx, Groucho’s son and daughter, as well as Morrie Ryskind, who authored four Marx brothers screenplays, including Animal Crackers and A Night at the Opera. After the performance, Arthur Marx approached him and asked if he would be interested in a play, Groucho: A Life in Revue, co-written by himself and TV writer Robert Fisher. A year later, Ferrante found himself off-Broadway at the Lucille Lortel Theatre in a run that lasted 254 performances. “I was 200 performances into it when that moment washed over me in which I realised I was in the moment. I felt like I was channeling the character,” he recalls about crossing the line from impersonation into acting. “Not a lot of actors get the chance to play a role for 200 shows. I’m one of those really fortunate theatre people in that I’ve actually worked consistently for the last 30 years in front of different kinds of audiences, trooping around like a vaudevillian.”It’s precisely what the Marx Brothers did. By the time they committed their act to film, they had honed the gags a hundred different ways in front of every type of audience, polishing it to the point that it seemed effortless. Introducing a unique brand of antic comedy that borders on the surreal (Salvador Dalí was friends with Harpo), they became reigning kings of comedy throughout the 30s and 40s. Even today their influence can be felt in acts running the gamut from Bugs Bunny to SNL. Ferrante won a 1987 New York Theatre World Award for A Life in Review before crossing the pond to the Comedy Theatre (now the Pinter) in London’s West End. “I didn’t know how the humour would translate, just as Groucho didn’t know back in the 1920s,” Ferrante said. “They would adjust their act to fit the sensibility. But we didn’t have to make any adjustment. All the papers gave it rave reviews. The audience was effusive. They loved the wordplay and the puns. This is the land that gave us Monty Python, and the Marx Brothers were certainly an influence on that kind of anarchic, surreal humour.”When he’s not cracking wise as Groucho, Ferrante portrays the flamboyant Latin lover, Caesar, in Teatro ZinZanni, a cirque-styled improvisational show in which he has shared the stage with singers such as Joan Baez and Liliane Montevecchi. The Seattle-based show will take him through the summer into autumn when he’ll begin rehearsals for a new production of Neil Simon’s Laughter on the 23rd Floor in Philadelphia. It will be a welcome respite from a character he’s been playing for over 30 years, but he hopes to keep playing Groucho for another 30. “I’m glad I get to facilitate some awareness of his greatness. The country’s been around for 200 years, and for half that time Groucho’s humour has been a part of our culture. What he represents as an outsider who tears it all down, takes down authority, it’s a beautiful thing to witness. There’s something edgy and dangerous about Groucho.”
</description>
<tags>
	stage,culture,comedy
</tags>