<seedurl>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us
</seedurl>
<url>
	http://www.theguardian.com/culture/2016/jan/09/extra-hot-great-podcast-tv-addicts
</url>
<title>
	Extra Hot Great: the podcast for TV addicts that's created its own community
</title>
<description>
	Founders (or longtime staffers) of the brilliant, but shuttered Television Without Pity website have made a podcast for ardent fans of TV – and quizzesThere are people who watch TV and then there are Television Fans – those among us who can endlessly debate the best moments from long defunct reality shows (Temptation Island, anyone?). Those who spend free time speculating about the fate of tertiary characters on Catfish, and who get into heated arguments about plot points on Hindsight. Extra Hot Great is the podcast for those ardent TV fans – or anyone who likes to laugh at the television. Extra Hot Great is the brainchild of David T Cole, Tara Ariano, Joe Reid and Sarah Bunting, who were all founders (or longtime staffers) of the brilliant, but shuttered Television Without Pity website. (Full disclosure, I wrote for the site years ago).Out of the ashes of Television Without Pity came the podcast, which featured Cole, Ariano and Reid talking about television and movies. When Cole and Ariano moved to LA, the podcast shutdown while they re-grouped. “We were thinking about Previously.TV as a site and a concept and we thought we would resurrect the podcast as part of that,” said Cole speaking of the entertainment website that he, Ariano and Bunting founded. “When we brought the podcast under the Previously umbrella, we brought in Sarah and then it was all about television.” They’ve been at it ever since, and just celebrated their fifth anniversary as a show.Making a podcast that is all about the minutia of television not only requires passion, but also a lot of TV watching. “Just for stuff that I cover, when everything is airing, I probably watch 20 hours a week,” said Bunting, that’s not including the auxiliary shows she watches when they are covered on the podcast, her true crime TV beat, nor the number of Beverly Hills 90210 episodes she watches for a spin-off website and podcast. “Tara probably watches twice as much as I do, ’cause she’s a supervillain, I guess?” said Bunting.Between the website, the podcast – mini-versions of which are released with astonishing frequency – and the television watching, television is their job. “Full-time, maybe time and a half,” said Bunting. It’s a dedication that shows in their podcast where they are able to discuss the finer points of shows from A to Z (remember that one?) to Zero Hour with everything in between. “It’s a lot of work,” admits Bunting, “But it’s a lot of fun. It’s in the service of doing something that we would be doing anyway, which is sitting around and talking about these shows, so why not have this be our job? Besides, there are limited options for an indoorsy TV obsessive like myself.”Extra Hot Great doesn’t just feature talking heads dryly pontificating on television. Instead, the show features a rotating cast of contributors and a seemingly endless stream of amusing motifs, whether they are starting a Law & Order Fantasy Draft team, ensemble casting their own podcast, hearing arguments on what TV show episodes should enter the canon, recasting TV characters as dogs, or entertaining wacky theories in the always popular I Am Not A Crackpot series, where fans try to make you a believer in their (not at all) crackpot ideas about TV shows. One place that the show really excels is getting its fans involved, whether suggesting quizzes, requesting topics or making a case for an episode to join the TV canon (or it’s opposite, the Nonac). “The podcast has been really great for getting people engaged, which is weird, because a podcast is kind of a passive product, but we have really good engagement,” said Cole. “It’s been kind of neat because I feel like I know the people who are the biggest fans of the podcast more than I know the fans of the editorial side of the site.”One of the most engaging elements of Extra Hot Great are the quizzes and games, which are a deep dive into TV fandom – and the psyche of the hosts. “The reason I got involved in the podcast is because I really wanted to do the game time part of it. I love doing the quizzes and listeners really responded to it,” said Cole.Fans of the podcast frequently make suggestions for Game Time topics, which the hosts really appreciate. “It’s always cool to see your idea coming back to you through somebody else, even better than you imagined,” said Cole. “The best part about the podcast for me is that even though we do this all day, everyday and watching TV can be a bit like a busman’s holiday at times, guests and fans make you think about different shows in different ways,” said Bunting. As for what types of games they play, they run the gamut. My favorite segment is ‘Is This Worse Than Jazz?’” said Cole. “It’s where you take something that is particularly terrible about something in television that is currently happening and compare it to the terribleness – in my opinion – that is jazz. We’ve never had one that is categorically worse than jazz.”“The only things that came close were a theme song that was jazz and Ken Burns’s Jazz,” said Bunting, “Nothing is worse than jazz.” Where to start: Pick your favorite TV show or dive right into The Canon.Subscribe to Extra Hot Great on iTunes
</description>
<tags>
	podcasting,culture,reality tv,television,television & radio
</tags>