<seedurl>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us
</seedurl>
<url>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2016/jan/08/missouri-floods-climate-change-weather-disaster-new-normal
</url>
<title>
	Missouri residents pack up and leave as once-rare floods become the new normal
</title>
<description>
	Deadly floods like the ones currently plaguing towns across the midwest, once labeled rare or freak weather events, are recurring with worrying regularityAbout 100 miles downstream of Hannibal, the boyhood home of Mark Twain, the small Missouri town of West Alton has spent the past week without almost its entire population as it has been completely swamped by water. William Richter is the mayor of a town he cannot reach. West Alton’s 525 people were evacuated due to deadly floods that caused the nearby Mississippi river to surge to 38ft high – a good 17ft above the flood level. Both roads into the town are still cut off.  “You can only really get in and out by tractor,” Richter says. “Either that or wade in but it’s hard because it’s cold and there’s ice. You want to get there and help people, but you can’t.” Richter thinks West Alton will lose around 20% of its population as residents decide to pack up and leave. It’s happened before – following widespread floods in 1993 the town’s population dropped by two-thirds. “There are some good people that just aren’t coming back,” he says. “The flooding has become just too much of an inconvenience. I really don’t want the community to die.”  The winter floods, of a scale unseen since the time a young Twain was on a skiff, caught Missouri a little by surprise. Tragically so – at least 24 people have died as a result of the floods so far, with many of these, including a group of overseas soldiers, perishing while trapped in their cars. With the water funneling downstream to southern states that have already declared pre-emptive states of emergency, this grim number is likely to climb. Heavy flooding isn’t meant to occur until spring, when the melting winter snows swell the rivers. Instead, hundreds of people saw in the new year enveloped in the Mississippi, houses marooned in muddy water, trees poking out like rice stalks. To many Missourians the culprit is clear – a hefty 10 inches of rain fell on east Missouri and west Illinois from Christmas onwards. But others are beginning to wonder whether some difficult choices need to be made in the face of an increasing number of flood events and the misery they cause, rather than simply brushing them off as a flinty reality of midwest life. In the past eight years, there have been three major flooding events on the Mississippi. The definition of what is considered a rare or freak flood is being stretched. Some residents feel their clean-ups are becoming a little too routine.  Hydrologist Bob Criss, of St Louis’s Washington University, recently studied flooding events in Hannibal. Every year between 2009 and 2015, bar one, Hannibal has experienced a flood that’s officially considered either a once in every 10-year or once in every 50-year event. “Our flood frequencies are way off. It’s absurd, a tragedy,” Criss says. “Every time, the authorities blame unusual rain events. It’s balderdash. We are just in denial.” Climate change is playing a role, with extreme downpours becoming more common in the midwest as moisture builds up in the atmosphere. US government scientists warned last year that heavy rainfall and flooding poses a growing risk to the midwest’s transportation, agriculture, human health and infrastructure. As if to underline this point, 2015 was the second wettest, as well as second warmest, year on record in the US. There are other factors, though. Criss blames a combination of risky property development in floodplain areas and a proliferation of levees in the 3,500-mile network of flood defenses along the Mississippi. The levees, barriers made from huge mounds of compacted soil and clay, are meant to divert surging river water to “natural backwater areas” rather than soak citizens.  But the scale of the network appears to be pushing large volumes of water up and invariably out of rivers – a study by Criss and the University of Oxford found that an 800-mile stretch of the Mississippi and Missouri rivers has halved in width since the beginning of the 20th century due to being hemmed in by levees. The US army corps of engineers, which administers the levees, didn’t respond to a request for comment. “The Mississippi should shrug off the rain but instead it’s acting like a little river because it’s being channeled by levees,” Criss says. “Flash flooding shouldn’t occur on one of the world’s great rivers. But the water has nowhere else to go but on to the heads of people who don’t have levees. You need levees for big cities but you can’t do it for 1,000 miles because the water needs somewhere to go.  “We seem to be oblivious to the effects of recurrent flooding. Whole neighborhoods were underwater in 1993, in 2008 and now again and we just rebuild in the same place. We’re amplifying flood frequency and damage. It’s the wrong approach. We need to wake up and smell the coffee.” In Arnold, Missouri, every other house has mounds of sodden furniture, children’s toys and carpet heaped on to muddy front yards. One homeowner has forlornly hauled a full, but ruined, drum kit outside. Another, Jon Thompson, 56, has enlisted the help of a roving band of volunteers to remove the contents of his recently renovated basement that was submerged by six feet of water in just one day.  “I had a 50-inch TV down there and everything,” Thompson says ruefully. “The water came through the sewers and I said to my wife: ‘We’ve got to get out of here.’ It lifted up the furniture and spun it around. The washer and drier were moving around, still connected to their hoses. That’s the power of water, really.”In the town of Arnold, the housing ends abruptly about 200 yards from the river after floods in 1993 caused waterside homes to be purchased and dismantled by the state government as a precaution that has, sadly, proved insufficient. Thompson admits to feeling “helpless” at floods that are causing some long-term residents to consider moving away, like they have in West Alton. The upheaval is wearing a little thin, even among those who have previously met floods with stoicism.  “Some people just accept this will happen, they are the ones with their trailers ready to take their things away,” he says. “I thought we had a once in 500 years flood in 1993 and we’d be OK. But we weren’t. Some of the people who first came to this neighborhood in 1959 are thinking about that. You’re hearing mumblings like: ‘You know what, it’s time to move.’ I think a lot of people will move.” Flood insurance, a decent income and help from friends, family and volunteers are the deciding factors on whether the flood-ravaged can get back on their feet. The government isn’t entirely invisible – the national guard has helped fill sandbags and purify water and the Federal Emergency Management Agency (Fema) is gearing up to provide assistance – but the frontline is largely manned by faith-based groups, mainly baptists and mennonites. Their trucks, with varying cross-centric logos, swarm around St Louis’s suburbs. In some cases this is enough. The town of Eureka, where 120 homes were damaged, has quickly bounced back thanks to an exemplary community effort. But others are less fortunate and find there is no one they can turn to. Nearly 700 people in the St Louis region took advantage of one of 13 Red Cross shelters in lieu of ruined homes. But the shelters are winding down now and without family or friends to fall back on, the handful of remaining residents are left in limbo. “This really is the Taj Mahal of shelters,” says Bob Kawka, head of the Red Cross shelter at the huge First Baptist church in Arnold. It has its own elevated jogging track which several displaced people use for their daily constitutionals. “But we are a lifeboat, not a love boat.” Uncertainty shrouds the life of Damon Thorne, an amiable 44-year-old man who lives with his mother Linda in a trailer park wedged between a freeway and the Meramac river, a tributary of the Mississippi that experienced record flooding over the new year. “The water came around the levees and in about an hour’s time it was ankle deep,” Thorne says. “It was scary. We got some bags of clothes but that was it. There was three feet of water in our trailer. It destroyed our furniture, everything really.” The Thornes’ abode is now a warped mess, its wooden floor having bent horribly our of shape, so they are temporarily staying in their landlord’s trailer. They had home insurance but it doesn’t cover floods. Their county didn’t supply sandbags and no volunteers are helping them out. “We felt like we were abandoned,” says Damon, who doesn’t work due to severe epilepsy. “We lost everything. We are trying to figure out where we go from here. How do we pick up from here? We are totally lost. “We are waiting for whatever the federal government can do. Being on a fixed income and disabled makes it hard. Right now we are just hoping for the best and leaving it in God’s hands.” Others, sadly, will share the Thornes’ fate over the coming week. The flooding surge is set to peak at 40ft in Memphis on Friday, falling to 17ft by the time it reaches New Orleans on 12 January. Preparations are already under way, including the piece-by-piece removal of the treasures of Vicksburg’s old depot museum to safer ground. Back in Arnold, Missouri, Jon Thompson is already planning where his new 50-inch TV will go once his insurance pays out. “I’ll stick it out a few more years here, I’ll get a new drywall and TV and everything and then I’ll retire and put it up for sale,” he says. “I’ll go and live on a mountain somewhere. I’d rather ski down than float up there.”
</description>
<tags>
	missouri,us news,flooding,environment,world news
</tags>