<seedurl>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us
</seedurl>
<url>
	http://www.theguardian.com/film/2016/jan/07/golden-globes-2016-film-awards-winner-prediction
</url>
<title>
	Golden Globe awards 2016: who will win, and who should win
</title>
<description>
	Compared to the Oscars, the Globes are unpredictable – and from Mad Max: Fury Road to The Martian, there are a wealth of great films up for this Sunday’s awardsAwards season kicks into high gear on Sunday with the 73rd annual Golden Globes, hosted for a fourth time by Ricky Gervais. The first major awards show of the year promises to be – as always – an unpredictable affair, with few clear frontrunners in the major film categories. The Hollywood Foreign Press Association, who vote for the awards, often don’t go with the tide: last year, the eventual best picture Oscar winner Birdman lost to Boyhood; in 2010, they opted for The Social Network over The King’s Speech, which went on to sweep the Oscars. Due to that factor, the Golden Globes usually make for a fun watch, spikier and less establishment than the Oscars. Ever since it first premiered at the Venice film festival, followed by triumphant debuts in Telluride and Toronto, Spotlight has been at the forefront of this season’s awards race. Tom McCarthy’s bracing account of the Boston Globe’s Pulitzer prize-winning investigation into a massive child molestation cover-up within the local Catholic archdiocese has already netted multiple critics’ awards, and nominations elsewhere. Spotlight received fewer Golden Globes nominations overall than Todd Haynes’s (superior) Carol, which dominated in the actress category for its two stars, but don’t expect that factor to threaten its chances. A Spotlight win could be potentially upset by George Miller’s Mad Max: Fury Road, which has surprised many to leap to the forefront of the pack in recent weeks, with a key win for best picture at the National Board of Review awards, on top of a coveted PGA award nomination for best picture.Will win: SpotlightShould win: Carol Related: The Big Short: how Wall Street's crimes have been portrayed by Hollywood Ridley Scott’s The Martian has been hailed as a comeback for the veteran director of such classics as Alien and Blade Runner, who in recent years disappointed with Prometheus and The Counselor. Critics embraced it and it was a major hit with audiences, grossing over $225m in the US alone – which led many to believe it had a shot at dominating awards season, despite being a science fiction film, a genre not generally popular with awards voters. Enter The Big Short, Adam McKay’s damning black comedy about the Wall Street crash of 2008, which seemingly came out of nowhere following a debut at the AFI film festival to pose a serious threat to all rivals. The film is timely and angry, boasts terrific performances from an all-star cast, and has since been awarded with major nominations from almost every top guild. In the comedy section at the Globes, it received the most nods with four. The odds are in its favour.Will win: The Big ShortShould win: The MartianThis was Ridley Scott’s to lose until Mad Max: Fury Road began to build up steam for its director, George Miller. And in all fairness, Miller is more deserving of the honour. In his triumphant return to the Mad Max franchise, Miller has reinvigorated the action genre to deliver some of the most daring and beautiful action sequences ever committed to celluloid, without sacrificing solid character development.Will win: George Miller, Mad Max: Fury RoadShould win: George Miller, Mad Max: Fury RoadLeonardo DiCaprio has said that playing a real-life 19th century explorer, who survives a brutal bear mauling in order to avenge the death of his son in The Revenant, was the hardest performance of his career. Watching Alejandro González Iñárritu’s brutal survival pic it’s easy to see why. Expect him to win simply for living to tell the tale of making the film. Yet Michael Fassbender is a more worthy winner for his complex portrayal of the titular Apple maverick in Steve Jobs (he also managed the tough feat of making Aaron Sorkin’s words his own), but don’t expect to hear the heartthrob’s name called.Will win: Leonardo DiCaprio, The RevenantShould win: Michael Fassbender, Steve JobsThis is the toughest race to call this year. Because it’s been such a landmark year for strong female performances, it’s near impossible to single out a standout among the pack. The odds are in Brie Larson’s favor to win for her committed performance as a kidnapped mother in Room, given the film has the advantage of a best picture nomination. But look out for Saoirse Ronan to possibly creep in, for her masterful work in the immigration drama Brooklyn. The two have been toe-to-toe all awards season, so it should prove interesting how this plays out.Will win: Brie Larson, RoomShould win: Saoirse Ronan, BrooklynMatt Damon deserves to win this category: his charismatic and emotional performance in The Martian is a true “star turn” if ever there was one. He’s all but guaranteed to triumph over The Big Short’s Christian Bale and Steve Carell, who really belong in the supporting category.Will win: Matt Damon, The MartianShould win: Matt Damon, The Martian Related: Lily Tomlin: ‘Women are forever the last recipients of progress’ Lily Tomlin delivers one of the best performances of her career in the tremendously moving comedy Grandma. Since its Sundance premiere last year, Tomlin has been gunning for awards glory with countless appearances on the circuit to tout the film and her lead turn. Expect her hard work to pay off. The only possible upset could be Amy Schumer, who had a hell of a year, and is tremendously effective in her smash comedy, Trainwreck.Will win: Lily Tomlin, GrandmaShould win: Lily Tomlin, GrandmaOut of the actors nominated in this category, Creed’s Sylvester Stallone has received the most attention for his comeback turn as a now retired Rocky Balboa. He’s quietly devastating in his performance, plus has never won a Globe, despite two prior nominations. Mark Rylance however is more of a standout for his heartrending and deftly comic work as a spy in Steven Spielberg’s period thriller, Bridge of Spies.Will win: Sylvester Stallone, CreedShould win: Mark Rylance, Bridge of SpiesNo actor in 2015 had more of a breakthrough year than Swedish star Alicia Vikander, who was everywhere, wowing in The Danish Girl, Ex Machina, Testament of Youth, and being smashing in The Man From Uncle. She’s favoured to win in this category for her haunting performance as a robot in Ex Machina, over her work in The Danish Girl, for which she was nominated in the best actress section. Jennifer Jason Leigh broke through in a different way last year, for returning to the fold in a major way with a ferocious turn in Quentin Tarantino’s The Hateful Eight.Will win: Alicia Vikander, Ex MachinaShould win: Jennifer Jason Leigh, The Hateful EightOut of the screenplays nominated, Aaron Sorkin’s dense Steve Jobs script is no doubt the showiest of the bunch. But he already won for The Social Network, and Steve Jobs has nowhere near the amount of goodwill on its part going into Sunday’s show as David Fincher’s Facebook drama. The Big Short has the momentum that Steve Jobs lacks, and is likely to be awarded for distilling a challenging book into an engaging narrative. Spotlight is less outright impressive than The Big Short in the writing department, but it’s arguably a leaner and more muted work – plus it’s been heralded by the Boston Globe for sticking very close to the facts.Will win: The Big ShortShould win: SpotlightCarter Burwell’s yearning score for Carol already feels like a classic. The same can’t be said for the competition.Will win: CarolShould win: CarolExpect the Globes to take the emotional route and award Fast and Furious 7 with Wiz Khalifa’s See You Again, its touching ode to the late Paul Walker. Fifty Shades of Grey could give it a run for its money with the equally popular Love Me Like You Do by Ellie Goulding.Will win: See You Again, Fast and Furious 7Should win: Love Me Like You Do, Fifty Shades of GreyFollowing a string of rare misfires with Monsters University, Brave and Cars 2, animation powerhouse Pixar made a triumphant comeback last summer with what’s been hailed by many as the studio’s best-ever film, Inside Out. It’s all but assured to win, although Charlie Kaufman’s ecstatically received first stab at animation, Anomalisa, is sure to resonate strongly with many voters. An upset is possible – and warranted.Will win: Inside OutShould win: AnomalisaSince its Cannes debut, where it won the festival’s runner-up prize, the Grand Prize of Jury, Laszlo Nemes’s holocaust drama Son of Saul has stunned all those brave enough to watch it. It should win every accolade for which it’s nominated, but given the immersive approach Nemes takes with his directorial debut, it’s unclear how voters will respond to it. France’s Mustang is tonally the complete opposite of Son of Saul: a true crowdpleaser, that boasts a big emotional payoff. It’s already won a handful of awards and audiences adore it, making it the safer win out of the pair.Will win: MustangShould win: Son of Saul
</description>
<tags>
	golden globes 2016,golden globes,film,culture,awards and prizes,spotlight,carol,mad max: fury road,the martian,the big short,the revenant,steve jobs,matt damon,lily tomlin,creed,son of saul
</tags>