<seedurl>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us
</seedurl>
<url>
	http://www.theguardian.com/football/live/2016/jan/09/manchester-united-sheffield-united-fa-cup-third-round-live
</url>
<title>
	Manchester United v Sheffield United: FA Cup third round – live!
</title>
<description>
	32 min: A ball looped down the Sheffield United right. Sharp has the jump on Borthwick-Jackson, and reaches the byline, though is low fizzer is cut out easily by Smalling.30 min: The pace has dropped. Blind tries to inject some impetus into proceedings with a burst through the middle. The ball’s shuttled right for Herrera, who near the corner flag tries to feed Darmian into the box. A harmless trundle along the byline rolls into the arms of Long.27 min: Fellaini pumps a long ball forward for Mata. Is this satire?25 min: Fellaini plays a piss-poor square pass in the midfield to gift Basham the ball. Basham tears down the inside-left channel, and would have broken into the box had Smalling not been positioned so well. A fine covering run from a class act. Fellaini owes him a bottle of something warming.23 min: A bit of space for Coutts down the right. His deep cross is headed behind by Darmian, with Sammon lurking. The corner leads to a Manchester United quickbreak through Martial, which fizzles out due to a lack of options. The home side, fed on rich, creamy spoonfuls during the Ferguson era, bellow their frustration. That’s doubled when a long ball’s pumped towards the head of Fellaini, and the big man misses it. Goal kick. Sheffield United will be very happy with the way this has gone so far.20 min: Rooney in the thick of the action. First he launches an absurd shot from just outside the area 30 yards over the bar. Then he’s sent scampering into the area down the inside-right channel, Sheffield United unpicked by a glorious pass down the flank from Darmian. Rooney takes the ball round Long on the outside, but leaves himself too tight an angle, and McEveley blocks the shot, or cross towards Martial, or whatever his intention was. Great defending.18 min: Long boots big down the middle of the park. Sammon brings the punt down brilliantly, lets the ball bounce, then lashes a rising screamer towards the top right from 25 yards. It’s a stunning shot, and well parried over the bar by De Gea. Sheffield United don’t get their corner, though, because the referee has spotted a Sammon hand ball. It wasn’t that obvious.17 min: Sheffield United are snapping into a few tackles right now, winning more than their fair share of 50-50s. Sammon makes a mighty nuisance of himself on the edge of the Manchester United area, then feeds Woolford down the left. De Gea plucks the cross from the sky.15 min: More of the Manchester United sterile possession. Sheffield United are holding their shape right now. “I’m disappointed that Louis Van Gaal hasn’t worn a trackie with two stripes today in a classic Cruyffian protest at the recent Adidas criticism of his team’s style,” writes Justin Kavanagh. “Dutch contrarianism isn’t what it once was, clearly!” Heh. You make a fair point. Though I’d have paid cash money to see the look of supreme disgust on Van Gaal’s face when he first heard about those comments.12 min: More possession for Borthwick-Jackson, who is in a can-do mood this evening. He wins a corner for his side down the left. A deep ball is headed up into the air twice by Fellaini, standing near the right-hand post, to little effect.11 min: Borthwick-Jackson finds a little space down the left, but his low cross is hooked away from danger by Edgar. Manchester United are beginning to dictate the game, in terms of possession anyway. They’re seeing a lot of the ball, but not doing a whole load with it.8 min: Mata waves his wand from wide on the right, very nearly dropping a diagonal curler onto the foot of Martial, cutting in from the left, 12 yards out. Not quite. But not far away.7 min: It’s probably best described as a fast-paced nonsense, so far, this game. The slippery surface, rain and wind will probably take a little getting used to. “Just wondering how Schneiderlin can be considered in the red zone, when he’s only played two games since 5th December,” wonders Mark Gillespie. You’d buy a used car off Louis van Gaal, that being the case, wouldn’t you.5 min: Sharp bothers Blind down the Sheffield United right. Blind very nearly lets his man go clear on goal, but recovers just in time and turns to clear. Up the other end, Martial takes Brayford on down the Manchester United left, and thinks he’s earned his team a corner, but the ball comes back off the young French star and out for a goal kick.4 min: A lot of loose balls being played by both teams at the moment. No shape to the game whatsoever.2 min: It’s a belting atmosphere at Old Trafford, both sets of supporters giving it plenty.Manchester United get the ball rolling. Sheffield United will kick towards the Stretford End in this first half. They lose the ball quickly enough, and Basham goes on a determined run from deep in his own half towards the midfield, before being upended by Fellaini in the centre circle. The free kick’s lumped forward, and sees Woolford romp down the left. He curls a powerful cross towards the near post, where De Gea gathers efficiently. Early signs that Sheffield United are going to give it a go, then.The teams are out! Manchester United are wearing their famous red, white and black, while Sheffield United sport their first-choice 125th-anniversary white shirts with red butcher’s stripes and super-retro badge. Both teams are an aesthetic delight. And the floodlights are shimmering through the heavy rain, so it’s quite a picture. FA Cup third-round football, right here! We’ll be off in a minute.An excitable Nigel Adkins talks! “It’s going to be a great occasion, eight-and-a-half thousand of our supporters here, the Theatre of Dreams. Manchester United should win the game, but let’s go and have a go at it, see what happens. Inspired is the word. This is where you want to play. Anybody can win on any given day. It’s the beauty of the cup. We’ve got to defend well, and have a lot of luck. We’re always likely to score goals. We’ve got spirit. We’re going to ask the question and make sure we enjoy it. Come the end of the game, we’ll get our recovery stretches done, and will be ready for Wigan on Tuesday!”LVG speaks of his love of the cup: “When I was a little boy I looked to the FA Cup, and certainly the final. I think I watched Jimmy Greaves, so it was a long time ago!” LVG speaks of naming a strong team: “Our experiences of last year make it clear that all games are difficult. I have no Ashley Young, but he is in the red zone because of the Christmas period. The same thing with Morgan Schneiderlin. I have to rotate. When I am not obliged to rotate, I don’t rotate.” LVG speaks on the potential of CBJ: “He did very well in his first game. To be consistent is difficult, and today he has to show he can be consistent.”Breaking news: It’s raining in Manchester.Louis van Gaal makes three changes to the side that beat Swansea City last weekend. Matteo Darmian, Cameron Borthwick-Jackson and Marouane Fellaini come in for Ashley Young, Phil Jones and Morgan Schneiderlin.Sheffield United, meanwhile, are unchanged from the XI sent out against Peterborough United seven days ago. Matt Done, in form until recently scuppered by a hamstring injury, is back on the bench.Manchester United: De Gea, Darmian, Smalling, Blind, Borthwick-Jackson, Schweinsteiger, Fellaini, Herrera, Mata, Martial, Rooney.Subs: Romero, McNair, Varela, Lingard, Pereira, Memphis, Keane.Sheffield United: Long, Brayford, Basham, Coutts, Sharp, Collins, Woolford, Sammon, McEveley, Edgar, Hammond.Subs: Howard, Flynn, Baxter, Done, Campbell-Ryce, Reed, Adams.Referee: Jon Moss (Tyne and Wear).Last season, Arsenal won the FA Cup. And so this happened to the all-time winners record...12: Arsenal 11: Manchester United 8: Tottenham Hotspur 7: Aston Villa, Liverpool, Chelsea 6: Blackburn Rovers, Newcastle United 5: Wanderers, West Bromwich Albion, Everton, Manchester CitySo will Manchester United strike back immediately? They’re due something in this famous old competition, certainly, for their recent record in the FA Cup is fairly poor. Relatively speaking, anyway. For anyone brought up between the late 1970s and early 1990s, when United hoovered up FA Cups at will, and those who got into football a little later, when United hoovered up absolutely everything at will, the last decade or so will have seemed a little strange. Since beating Millwall to lift their 11th cup in 2004, they’ve reached the final twice, and the semis on another two occasions. Not a bad record at all by most club’s standards. Not so good by Manchester United’s, though.Plenty of reason for them to go for it this season, then. And fold into the mix the storied career of Louis van Gaal. Nothing’s certain at Old Trafford right now, and it’s possible this could be his last season at the club. A victory in the FA Cup would be some way to go out. You’d have a heart of stone not to enjoy him lifting a trophy as a symbolic stiff-fingered salute to the media, after the relentless disrespectful nonsense he’s had to put up with this season. In a perfect world, he’d be doing it thanks to a series of victories on penalty kicks after grinding 0-0 draws.But Manchester United aren’t the only club allowed to dream their dreamy dreams. Sheffield United have won this trophy four times themselves, and are really due a little something coming their way: their last victory was in 1925. They’re currently eighth in League One, and in very decent nick. They’ve won four of their last five games, and scored twice in the single match they lost during that sequence. They’ll also be buoyed by their recent record against higher-ranked opponents in the cup - they’ve won five of the last six - and will retain strong memories of a famous win over Manchester United in the 1993 edition of this tournament.Manchester United, for their part, have lost just the once to a lower-ranked side in the FA Cup in the last 36 ties. Hats off to Leeds United, who put them out here in January 2010. They also repaid the Blades for that 1993 defeat with victories in 1994 and 1995. They’ll be hot favourites to register another win this evening, of course, though they’ll have to do without Adnan Januzaj, freshly returned from his Borussia Dortmund loan short of match fitness, while Sheffield United might be able to recall striker Matt Done after a hamstring injury.The first step towards Manchester United’s first FA Cup since 2004? Or the first step towards Sheffield United’s first FA Cup since 1925? We’ll soon find out (unless it goes to a replay, but let’s not muddy the waters unnecessarily). It’s on!Kick off: 5.30pm.
</description>
<tags>
	fa cup,manchester united,sheffield united,football,sport
</tags>