<seedurl>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us
</seedurl>
<url>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2016/jan/08/california-surfers-el-nino-waves
</url>
<title>
	California surfers take advantage of big El Niño waves
</title>
<description>
	Mavericks, along the San Mateo County coast, is known to form some of the biggest and most dangerous waves in the worldDozens of big-wave surfers rode 50ft swells at Mavericks, a famous surf spot in northern California, as El Niño-driven storms pounded the California coast on Friday.Mavericks, along the San Mateo County coast, is known to form some of the biggest and most dangerous waves in the world, and is home to the Titans of Mavericks big wave competition. “These are some of the biggest waves I’ve seen at Mavericks in three years, and yesterday I caught what was probably a 25ft wave,” said Travis Payne, 31, a professional big-wave surfer from nearby Pacifica. The day before, pro surfer Garrett McNamara, who holds the world record for riding the biggest wave at 100ft, reportedly dislocated his shoulder at Mavericks when he fell off his board and was hit by a massive wave. “El Niño is a double-edged sword for surfers – it brings more storms, brings the storms closer to us and big waves. But it can also bring the wrong kind of winds, which can be dangerous,” Payne said.He added that this week’s storms came with light winds from the north, which at Mavericks helps surfers nicely glide down the face of a huge wave. Most surfers at Mavericks this week were locals, but that will change if El Niño-related storms pick up this winter; more storms are expected next week.“I was watching the storms but the conditions being right for big-wave surfing came all of a sudden,” Payne said. “I don’t think other surfers had time to fly out here to surf these waves.”Thwen Chaloemtiarana, a surfer and employee at the Mavericks Surf Shop, said that the big waves were not for everyone. “You need the right skills for these waves, they can be dangerous,” he said.
</description>
<tags>
	california,el niño southern oscillation,us weather,environment,us news
</tags>