<seedurl>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us
</seedurl>
<url>
	http://www.theguardian.com/music/2016/jan/09/lemmy-memorial-service-live-stream-hollywood
</url>
<title>
	Lemmy fans gather for memorial service live-streamed from Hollywood
</title>
<description>
	‘Motörheadbangers’ around the world invited to toast the life of legendary bass player on day of celebration at musician’s favorite Los Angeles barFriends and fans of Ian “Lemmy” Kilmister, the frontman of Motörhead, were scheduled to gather in Hollywood for the legendary bassist’s memorial service on Saturday, as well as for a day of celebration at his favorite Los Angeles bar. Related: Mötorhead's Lemmy stars in milk ad released weeks after his death The memorial service and “toast” to the musician, whose career spanned half a century, was to be live-streamed starting at 3pm PST (6pm ET, 11pm GMT). Organizers invited all “fellow Motörheadbangers and friends” around the world to celebrate Kilmister’s life.“Whatever your venue, and however you can, let’s be sure to gather globally on Saturday 9th and celebrate the life of our dear friend and irreplaceable icon,” a message read.Kilmister’s funeral will be a private service at the Forest Lawn Memorial Cemetery, where Michael Jackson, Walt Disney, Humphrey Bogart and others are buried. He died on 26 December, aged 70, only two days after receiving a diagnosis of an aggressive form of cancer. Despite his age and an accomplished career, Kilmister continued touring and recording albums until the end. Motörhead released their 22nd studio album, Bad Magic, last year, and in an interview with the Guardian around its release he joked that a lifetime of living to extremes – and a dangerous surgery in 2013 – could not stop him: “Apparently I am still indestructible.” The bassist won many friends around the music world, including Ozzy Osbourne, who tweeted his tribute: “Lost one of my best friends, Lemmy, today. He will be sadly missed. He was a warrior and a legend. I will see you on the other side.”Megadeth lead singer and guitarist Dave Mustaine tweeted: “Farewell Lemmy. I love you brother.”Born in Staffordshire in 1945, Kilmister variously worked as a roadie for Jimi Hendrix and played for Hawkwind and Sam Gopal before founding Motörhead. His hoarse, raging vocals and frenetic but precise bass work became nearly inextricable from metal as a genre, but the bassist himself refused to be penned in by any category. Lyrics about war and abuse mingled with blunt rock songs about having a good time on Motörhead records, and Lemmy himself, with mutton chops, long hair and a love of Nazi memorabilia, refused to conform even to the stereotypes of rock.
</description>
<tags>
	lemmy,music,los angeles,california,us news
</tags>