<seedurl>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us
</seedurl>
<url>
	http://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/jan/09/north-korea-says-souths-propaganda-broadcasts-taking-it-to-brink-of-war
</url>
<title>
	North Korea says South's propaganda broadcasts taking it to 'brink of war'
</title>
<description>
	Senior party official says rivals are ‘jealous’ of Pyongyang’s nuclear test as Seoul places troops near loudspeakers on high alertA senior North Korea party official warned of war in a speech on Saturday as South Korea continued blasting anti-Pyongyang propaganda across the border in retaliation for the North’s fourth nuclear test. Related: Bang bang bang! The K-pop songs being blasted into North Korea Speaking to a massive crowd at Pyongyang’s Kim Il-sung Square, a top ruling party official said the broadcasts – along with talks between Washington and Seoul on the possibility of deploying nuclear bombers in the South – have pushed the Korean Peninsula “toward the brink of war”.Pyongyang’s rivals were “jealous” of the North’s claimed successful hydrogen bomb test, Workers’ party secretary Kim Ki Nam said in comments broadcast on state TV late Friday.North Korean propaganda is filled with warnings of war, and the country is sensitive to criticism of its authoritarian leadership, which Seoul resumed in its cross-border broadcasts on Friday for the first time in nearly five months. Pyongyang has previously said the broadcasts were tantamount to an act of war. When South Korea briefly resumed propaganda broadcasts in August after an 11-year break, Seoul said the two Koreas exchanged artillery fire.South Korea’s Yonhap news agency reported that frontline South Korean troops, near 11 sites around the loudspeakers, were on highest alert. Yonhap said Seoul had deployed missiles, artillery and other weapons systems near the border to swiftly deal with any possible North Korean provocation. South Korea’s defence ministry did not confirm the reports.While the South’s broadcasts also include news and pop music, much of the programming challenges North Korea’s government more directly.“We hope that our fellow Koreans in the North will be able to live in [a] society that doesn’t invade individual lives as soon as possible,” a female presenter said in parts of the broadcast that officials revealed to South Korean media. “Countries run by dictatorships even try to control human instincts.”The broadcasts came as world powers sought to find other ways to punish the North for conducting a nuclear test on Wednesday.US Secretary of State John Kerry urged China, the North’s only major ally and its biggest aid provider, to end “business as usual” with North Korea.Diplomats at a UN security council emergency session pledged to swiftly pursue new sanctions. For current sanctions and any new penalties to work, better cooperation and stronger implementation from China is seen as key.South Korean and US military leaders also have discussed the deployment of US “strategic assets”, Seoul’s defence ministry said. Officials refused to elaborate, but the assets are likely to be B-52 bombers, F-22 stealth fighters and nuclear-powered submarines.After North Korea’s third nuclear test in 2013, the US took the unusual step of sending its most powerful warplanes – B-2 stealth bombers, F-22 stealth fighters and B-52 bombers – to take part in drills with South Korea in a show of force. B-2 and B-52 bombers are capable of delivering nuclear weapons.It may take weeks or longer to confirm or refute the North’s claim that it successfully tested a hydrogen bomb, which would mark a major and unanticipated advance for its still-limited nuclear arsenal. Outside experts are skeptical the blast was a hydrogen bomb, but even a test of an atomic bomb would push North Korea closer to building a nuclear warhead small enough to place on a long-range missile.Late Friday, the Korea Institute of Nuclear Safety said a small amount of radioactive elements was found in air samples collected from the peninsula’s eastern seas after the blast but the measured amount was too small to determine whether the North had really detonated a nuclear device.The institute said the level of xenon-133 isotopes found in the samples was similar to levels normally detected at its two radioactive gas detectors on the eastern and western coasts. KINS official Lee Ki-hyeong also noted that other types of xenon isotopes used to confirm nuclear explosions weren’t detected.Lee said the institute would continue to collect and analyze more samples.The British foreign secretary, Philip Hammond, had asked South Korea to refrain from the propaganda broadcasts. But South Korea sees K-pop and propaganda as quick ways to show its displeasure – and a guaranteed irritant to the North’s sensitive and proud leadership.The broadcasts include Korean pop songs, world news and weather forecasts as well as criticism of the North’s nuclear test, its troubled economy and dire human rights conditions, according to Seoul’s defence ministry.Performers on Seoul’s propaganda playlist include a female K-pop band that rose to fame when its members fell multiple times on stage, a middle-aged singer who rose from obscurity in 2015 with a song about living for 100 years and songs by a young female singer, IU, whose sweet voice might be aimed at North Korean soldiers deployed near the border.North Koreans are prohibited from listening to K-pop, but defectors have said their countrymen enjoy music and other elements of South Korea popular culture that are smuggled into the country on USB sticks and DVDs.
</description>
<tags>
	north korea,south korea,asia pacific,nuclear weapons
</tags>