<seedurl>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us
</seedurl>
<url>
	http://www.theguardian.com/film/2016/jan/08/golden-globes-2016-preview-mel-gibson
</url>
<title>
	Golden Globes: thank you, famous people, for embarrassment, insincerity … and Mel
</title>
<description>
	The ‘edgy host’, the fashion disasters, the fact they serve alcohol – Sunday’s ceremony has a lot of things other shows lack. Including, this year, Mel GibsonThe Golden Globes, the Liam Hemsworth of Hollywood awards shows, returns on Sunday night for yet another year of sloppy, gin-soaked glad-handing. Related: Golden Globes 2016: who will win, and who should win the TV categories There was once a time where the Golden Globes were rightly treated as the slapdash afterthought they really are. Do you remember who won the Golden Globe for best motion picture, drama in 2003? The Hours! A fine film, but I can’t think there’s many people making that their Netflix and chill movie of choice. Of course, this is the Guardian and you’re an educated, intellectual sort, so maybe you do. But in the wider, cheeseburger-and-fries culture of America, these awards shows are mostly disposable and exist solely for the purpose of advertising films the average moviegoer will never see. In other words, no one is talking about Spotlight in the parking lot of a Bass Pro Shop, but maybe the Golden Globes will convince them to see it when it comes to their local 30-screen multiplex/outdoor mall/feed barn.As two-hour-long commercials go, the Globes always possessed one advantage over the Oscars – they serve alcohol, which means the potential for famous people humiliating themselves increases tenfold. In the past few years, that novelty has become more and more important to the advertising appeal of the event. The “edgy host”, the flubbed pre-written banter and the drunken buffoonery of usually controlled movie stars turned the Golden Globes from a little-seen Oscar precursor to a cultural attraction in its own right. But it’s all predicated on something embarrassing happening to someone rich and/or attractive. I guess that’s most unscripted television these days – Vanderpump Rules, The Bachelor and the various presidential debates are all exercises in schadenfreude. We point and laugh because, to be frank, it’s increasingly cathartic in a world that seems beyond the control of normal people. Thank God for Steve Harvey announcing the wrong winner at the Miss Universe pageant. If he hadn’t, I might have had to think about the natural gas leak a few miles from my apartment melting the ozone layer or the sectarian massacres taking place a couple continents away. Thank you, famous people! I’d probably have stuck my head in an oven if it wasn’t for you mispronouncing someone’s name. It’s comforting to know that you really are “just like me” – you also hate to be sober at a shit party.Here, then, is a list of ignominious moments we have to look forward to during Sunday’s celebration of the arts-slash-mortifying, televised live disaster. With it, you’ll be guaranteed to not miss a single moment of delicious, blood-curdling horror: Related: Golden Globe awards 2016: who will win, and who should win Mel’s been a de facto nonentity in Hollywood since he was taped, on two occasions, making racist and antisemitic remarks. Industry heavyweights put on a show of how disgusted they were by his hate speech – taking out ads in the trades and ostensibly blacklisting him for years. Every so often, some celebrity would ask, “Hey, remember Mel Gibson? We should forgive him!” That would go nowhere because who wants to spend millions of dollars on a movie and risk alienating a large swath of the audience by employing someone with a toxic reputation? Well, Mad Max: Fury Road came out to great acclaim and we all asked: “Hey, where’s Mel Gibson? Didn’t he play Mad Max once?” He popped up at the premiere and did some press, putting him back in something resembling the spotlight. The movie was a financial success and is nominated for best motion picture, drama at the Globes this year.So, like, why not bring Mel out? Besides the peculiar sight of people clapping for him and the attendant message that sends to the world, I guess there’s no reason not to. Hopefully he says something insane.Here’s a can’t-miss recipe for an unpleasant live TV moment: take one petrified ingenue, put her onstage in front of millions of viewers at home in a room full of weird, powerful men who work in an industry known for grinding young women into a gelatinous paste-like substance and drinking it with dinner. This year’s sacrifice is Corinne Foxx, daughter of Jamie Foxx. She might turn out to be a huge success like former winners Dakota Johnson and Laura Dern – or she could end up like Candace Savalas, daughter of Telly Savalas, aka TV’s Kojak.Fun fact: sometimes, they give this honor to a man. In 1996, Freddie Prinze Jr was named Mr Golden Globes. Not long after, Prinze Jr was starring in Wing Commander and the Scooby Doo movies, so you know this thing is prestigious.Wiz Khalifa.Those pre-shows always pretend to be about spotlighting the most striking sartorial choices on the red carpet, but that’s a bit of misdirection. It’s actually just a pretense for catching some poor rube who didn’t realize they wore a purple Hefty bag with a bow tie on their ass to an awards show. The biggest “fashion victims” at awards shows are usually a) a writer, because lord knows we don’t know how to dress ourselves; b) someone who’s never been nominated for a single award in their life until now, like an elderly person or a child; or c) someone foreign. We love mocking people from other countries, with their “weird languages” and “names with more than two vowels in them”. Watch out, Ryuichi Sakamoto – Melissa Rivers is going to ruin your night. Related: Golden Globes 2016: the start of the red-carpet arms race There’s a grand tradition of awkward spills at awards shows, but the Globes is the most hazardous event of them all. The combination of drink, uncomfortable formal wear and nerves mean that at least one celebrity is going to take a tumble. You can either be “adorkable” à la Jennifer Lawrence at the Oscars and make that a major part of your personal brand going forward, or you can find yourself named and shamed like Jennifer Lopez at the 2009 American Music Awards.If I had to guess who’s going to fall I’d say, again, Wiz Khalifa. In general, keep your eyes on Wiz Khalifa all night because the chances of him traversing the red carpet or accepting an award for best original song on a hoverboard are very, very strong. In fact, if he doesn’t ride a hoverboard at some point during the show, I’ll boycott the Golden Globes every year until he does. That’s a promise. He owes us.
</description>
<tags>
	golden globes 2016,mel gibson,golden globes,entertainment,awards and prizes,culture,film,television
</tags>