<seedurl>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us
</seedurl>
<url>
	http://www.theguardian.com/football/2016/jan/09/arsenal-sunderland-fa-cup-match-report
</url>
<title>
	Olivier Giroud puts seal on Arsenal’s Cup win against Sunderland
</title>
<description>
	The two-time holders are through to the fourth round of the FA Cup after a low-pressure, intermittently urgent 3-1 defeat of Sunderland at the Emirates. A changed, but not overly-changed Arsenal team took its moments to strike, with second-half goals from Aaron Ramsey and Oliver Giroud sealing the tie. Alex Iwobi made a promising first start in the competition. And Arsenal’s attempt to become the first team since Blackburn 130 years ago to win the FA Cup three times in a row remains, for now, on course.Beyond that, in the world of modern footballing realpolitik, this was a result that probably suited both teams. Sunderland took the lead here, and played with energy throughout but in the build up to this game Sam Allardyce had railed against the round of Premier League fixtures scheduled for Tuesday night. It is easy enough to see his point. For Sunderland January is a tipping point in the league, with a run of three eminently winnable matches against Aston Villa, Swansea and Bournemouth. With this in mind Allardyce’s starting XI was a stripped back affair, with seven changes from their last Premier League game, including 21-year-old Jordan Pickford, who made a fine club debut in goal.Arsène Wenger had spoken in the week about the need to respect the competition, the lure of its enduring magic and so on. There is an agreeable oddity in a manager who was once seen as the vanguard of annihilating overseas modernism, emerging as a guardian of English football’s grandest, most faded and outflanked competition. But then, Wenger has been around a terribly long time, a manager who was out there winning epic semi-final replays when the Cup was still the Cup.He put out a strong team here too with the only concession to the occasion a second start for Iwobi, a long term academician but a genuine talent and a full Nigeria international. Mesut Özil was granted a long overdue rest. Chris Willock, another academy player said to be coveted by Barcelona last summer, made his first appearance on the bench in a team-sheet with five players aged 20 or under.Iwobi made a bright start, playing to the left of central midfield in a 4-1-4-1, with Callum Chambers hoovering up behind and Giroud the lone striker. It was down Iwobi’s flank that Kieran Gibbs had the first real sight of goal, cutting in and shooting at a good height for Pickford to palm the ball over.With 17 minutes gone Gibbs was also involved in the opening goal at the other end, losing the ball under pressure from Jermain Lens. Behind him Laurent Koscielny, surprised by the break of the ball, also lost it, also to Lens, who shot past Petr Cech. It was a poor goal to concede, but also a victory for Lens’s energy and opportunism.Arsenal were level six minutes later. It was a lovely goal too. Iwobi, driving through the inside left channel, played a nice nudged pass to Theo Walcott, who feinted for the byline then played a beautiful cutback for Campbell to finish with relaxed assurance.After which Arsenal settled into a series of low pressure probings, with Iwobi, Walcott, Campbell and Oxlade-Chamberlain linking well enough, while Lens did his best to lead Sunderland on the counterattack. The same pattern resumed after half-time as Arsenal pressed a little harder, with the urgent Iwobi again giving the impression this was a match that perhaps meant a little more to him than some others on the pitch.With 12 minutes of the second half gone, and the prospect of a reply beginning to lurk dimly, the game sprung to life. Oxlade-Chamberlain hit the post after making some space with a jink on the edge of the box. Pickford made an excellent, brave close-range save from Campbell, and in between times Steven Fletcher hit the bar with a header from close range when it seemed easier to score .With 20 minutes to go Mikel Arteta and Aaron Ramsey came on and Arsenal began to press down the flanks, with Giroud and Walcott twice failing to make good contact with low fizzed crosses from the left. It was from the right that the second goal came, Héctor Bellerín frolicking in behind Patrick van Aanholt and providing a perfect cutback for Ramsey to angle the ball delicately from close range past Pickford.Two minutes later the same route to goal sealed the game, Bellerín again cutting in with great poise and finding Giroud in the middle to sidefoot the ball home.
</description>
<tags>
	fa cup,arsenal,sunderland,football,sport
</tags>