<seedurl>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us
</seedurl>
<url>
	http://www.theguardian.com/culture/2016/jan/09/lena-dunham-hillary-clinton-policies-pantsuits-iowa
</url>
<title>
	Lena Dunham talks policies and pantsuits in push for Hillary Clinton
</title>
<description>
	In Iowa, Girls creator and star rejects ‘condescending’ and ‘misogynistic’ assumption she backs Democratic frontrunner just because she is a womanLena Dunham isn’t supporting Hillary Clinton for president because they share the same anatomy. She is, however, a big fan of the Democratic frontrunner’s pantsuits. Related: Lena Dunham asks Hillary Clinton: are you a feminist? 'Yes, absolutely' Dunham, the star and creator of HBO’s Girls, laid out her support for Clinton at two events in Iowa on Saturday, while urging crowds of mostly women to get involved in the Iowa caucus on 1 February. “Nothing gets me angrier than when someone implies I’m voting for Hillary Clinton simply because she’s female,” said Dunham at her first event of the day, to laughter. “[It’s] as if I have some feminist version of beer-goggles, lets call it ‘estrogen blindness’, and I just kind of walk like a zombie towards the nearest vagina. This assumption is condescending at best and it is sharply misogynistic at worst.”Dunham said she was supporting Clinton “because of her policies, because of her track record, because of her beliefs – and a little bit because of her pantsuits. But that’s my prerogative as a citizen.”The actress has been a vocal supporter of Clinton for much of the candidate’s second run for the presidency, and has been known to drop by campaign headquarters in Brooklyn. Dunham recently interviewed Clinton for the first issue of her email newsletter, Lenny. Seated across from Clinton on a folding chair, she asked the Democratic candidate: “Do you consider yourself a feminist?” “Yes,” Clinton responded. “Absolutely.”With her trademark mix of raw candor and playful self-deprecation, on Saturday Dunham told the crowd how she had not voted until four years after she came of voting age. She encouraged women, especially young women, to make their voices heard in 2016. “I’m embarrassed to say this but it took me far too long to start voting,” Dunham said. “I had been of legal age for more than four years before I cast my first vote in the 2008 presidential election. “It’s not that I didn’t care, but I didn’t believe that me caring mattered. It was impossible for me to comprehend that one young woman checking a box after waiting in a long line could matter on a national level.”Dunham said she almost turned down the opportunity to create a video for President Barack Obama’s re-election campaign in 2012. She said deciding to make the innuendo-laced film, Your First Time, energized her to engage with politics.“My father has never been prouder of me than when I was called a dirty word on Fox News,” Dunham joked about reaction to the video, which she said went “a little bit viral”.The campaign also promoted a chance for Iowa supporters to meet Dunham, raffling off a lunch date to supporters who signed up for the campaign’s text updates. The woman who won the contest, Sarah Hinchliff Pearson, published an open letter to Dunham, expressing her admiration. On Friday, Dunham traveled around New Hampshire with the World Cup-winning soccer superstar Abby Wambach, pitching Clinton as the best advocate for women and the best candidate for the White House. Notably, Dunham has been having fun with her bespoke Hillary Clinton line of dresses and sweaters. In Iowa on Saturday, she wore a white jumper featuring “Hillary” printed in red.The trips seemed aimed at young women, a seemingly natural fit for Clinton’s message. But recent polls have shown an age gap between Clinton and supporters of Bernie Sanders, the Vermont senator winning more support from people under 45. In Iowa the audience, equal parts Dunham fans and Clinton supporters, were very receptive. Abbie Gould, 24, said she was still deciding between Clinton and Sanders, but was impressed by what Dunham had to say.“Listening to Lena, hearing the sincerity in her voice and listening to how she got involved in the campaign, and that she actually hadn’t gotten involved into politics until later in her career, I think that’s inspiring for people my age,” Gould said. Related: Hillary Clinton issues stern rebuke to Bernie Sanders on gun control record Allison Poss, who runs a small business, Girls with Ideas, in Iowa City, called Dunham and Clinton the “dream team”. Poss said she was an unabashed Dunham fan – she collects clippings of every magazine interview she gives – and a longtime Clinton supporter.“I’ve always followed [Clinton’s] policies, that is what is driving my vote for her,” she said, after the event at a coffee shop in Iowa City. “However, it’s like a double-whammy of happiness to me that she just so happens to be a woman as well.”Maggie Mineart, 26, said Dunham’s message really resonated with her, and that she “appreciated having someone who is a peer, or pretty close to a peer” speak about the issues that are important this election, including paid family leave and healthcare.“It would be cool to have a woman president, but that’s not why I would vote for her,” Minearet said after the event at a screen printing studio in Des Moines. “If I wanted to just vote for a woman, I could vote for Carly Fiorina too, but I’m not.”Mineart said she was still deliberating over the top two Democratic contenders and planned to attend a Sanders campaign event in Iowa later that evening. Of Dunham, Mineart added: “Oh – her outfit was really on point.”
</description>
<tags>
	lena dunham,culture,hillary clinton,democrats,us politics,us elections 2016
</tags>