<seedurl>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us
</seedurl>
<url>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2016/jan/09/the-crying-game-obama-tears-politicians
</url>
<title>
	The crying game: how political tears became routine
</title>
<description>
	At one time tears could finish a political career, but now crying is an important tool in the campaign armourySome ingenious theories have gone around this week about Barack Obama’s tears. That he wipes his eyes in a suspicious direction (inwards). That he wipes before the tears are visible (he is in fact stimulating them with a dab of menthol). That he is a suspiciously good actor (and thus probably a psychopath). In attacking Obama on this point, however, his opponents also concede something interesting: that his tears, if genuine, do him credit.Public crying is a loss of control – perhaps not a shameful loss, perhaps endearing – but always a brief weakness, a disruption from within. As a result, it has often been considered a serious political error. When it was reported that Ed Muskie, the frontrunner for the Democratic nomination in 1972, had cried while defending himself and his family from media attacks, his support collapsed. Even Margaret Thatcher was denounced for feebleness in 1978, when she admitted that she sometimes cried at home after a bad day.As these examples show, however, context is everything. Muskie’s tears, like Howard Dean’s scream of 2004 or Neil Kinnock’s inept rabble-rousing of 1992, were moments of weakness that seemed to fit weak people. No one could ever plausibly say that of Thatcher, who could retain an iron reputation even after a TV interview she gave in 1985 in which she discussed growing up with “Mummy” and “Daddy” and became the first British prime minister to cry on screen. The memory that provoked her, intriguingly, was her father being forced from his post in local government – prefiguring her own later tears on leaving Downing Street. (I can find no record of Tony Blair, considered far more emotionally literate, ever crying publicly.)Today, perhaps because it is better understood, political crying is almost routine. David Cameron cried while being praised by William Hague, John Bercow on being re-elected speaker, George Osborne at Thatcher’s funeral. Even Vladimir Putin cried during a victory rally in Red Square. Each of the past three US presidents has publicly shed tears while in office, Obama at least five times.In fact, crying can be a tremendous boost to politicians, because it marks a rare moment when we can be sure of their sincerity (menthol aside). When Obama cries over murdered children, or the devotion of his staff, he is showing compassion for others and humility – precisely the “weaknesses” that one would want in a leader. He is also very controlled, preferring to pause rather than let his voice crack, wiping away tears if necessary, but soldiering on. Compare this with the former Brazilian president Luiz Inácio Lula da Silva, who was incapacitated by the news that Rio had won the Olympics, bawling for some time into his handkerchief. Or with Australia’s former prime minister Julia Gillard, whose tears over the death of her father and the suffering of disabled people were admirable, but which nevertheless became a prolonged spectacle of weakness, as she struggled to control her voice.Angela Merkel has never been filmed crying, as far as I can tell, but this suits her character. She appears not to need sympathy, but instead became famous for offering it, last July, to a 14-year-old Palestinian girl who burst into tears during a TV debate.Perhaps no politician has benefited from crying more clearly than Hillary Clinton. In January 2008, in a New Hampshire diner, having fallen behind Obama in the race for the Democratic nomination, she was bowled just about the gentlest question imaginable: “How do you keep upbeat and so wonderful?” But it seemed to catch her mood. “I couldn’t do it if I didn’t passionately believe it was the right thing to do,” she began. “I’ve had so many opportunities from this country, I just don’t want to see us fall backwards, you know.” Then her voice tailed off. It was self-pity, yes. But showing her hurt feelings proved to a doubting public that she had some; then she, too, soldiered on. She won New Hampshire, but lost the nomination. No one called her soft, and it looks like she’ll be back.
</description>
<tags>
	barack obama,us news,us politics,margaret thatcher,politics,world news
</tags>