<seedurl>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us
</seedurl>
<url>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2016/jan/07/oregon-standoff-militia-leader-ammon-bundy-sheriff-meeting
</url>
<title>
	Militia leader Ammon Bundy defiant after showdown with Oregon sheriff
</title>
<description>
	The leader of the armed militia occupying the federal wildlife refuge vowed to continue the standoff after a head-to-head with the local sheriffAmmon Bundy, the leader of the armed occupation of a wildlife refuge in eastern Oregon, met for a showdown with the local county sheriff late on Thursday amid signs that at least some in his militia want their controversial standoff to draw to a close.In what appeared to be a pre-arranged rendezvous, Bundy met with Harney County sheriff Dave Ward on a remote road 15 miles away from the federal buildings the militiamen have occupied since Saturday.It was the first time the pair met since the occupation began. They made no agreements about a possible resolution to the standoff. “We plan on staying,” Bundy told reporters following a meeting. “I’m not afraid to go out of state. I don’t need an escort.”Ward, who has been the subject of death threats since the armed militia entered his county, has publicly pleaded for the anti-government protesters to leave the Malheur wildlife refuge and appears to have the backing of the local community.Although the short meeting opened a new line of communication between local law enforcement and the militia, it remains unclear how and when the high-profile occupation will come to an end.The conversation, which Bundy said lasted less than 10 minutes, came as tensions continued to escalate at the refuge and in Burns, the closest town to the occupation. News of the meeting sent reporters stationed at the refuge scrambling to attend, a handful speeding down the road and dozens eventually tripping over each other and falling on the icy, snow-covered ground to get Bundy’s reaction. Ward said he was hoping for a peaceful resolution and was willing to escort the protesters out of Oregon.According to two Reuters reporters present at the meeting, Ward told Bundy that he was seeking a peaceful resolution to the nearly week-long standoff and offered to escort the occupiers out of Oregon.But Bundy, the son of Cliven Bundy, whose cattle ranch in Nevada became the focus of a similar standoff in 2014, declined, saying that the sheriff had not addressed the occupiers’ grievances.Back at the refuge, as the sun started to set and temperatures began to drop in the remote federal outpost in rural Oregon, Bundy told reporters and a group of his supporters crowded around a fire that he has no timeline for when the occupation will end. But he insisted Ward would need to address the group’s complaints.The standoff near the town of Burns has been a magnet for a trickle of militia men from across the country, in a dispute that began over the imprisonment of two local ranchers but quickly spiraled into a broader battle over land rights.“There’s something much bigger here that needs to be resolved,” Bundy told those present. “And until we know and understand that the people are going to end up on top here, we plan on staying.”At a community meeting in Burns on Wednesday, residents asked Ward to tell the occupiers in person that they need to leave. The FBI and other federal law enforcement are closely monitoring the situation but are holding back from a confrontation, fearing it could spark violence.Earlier on Thursday, even some of the protesters who say they support the message of the occupation were also expressing doubts about the continued standoff with no end in sight.“I’m here today to take people home and try to encourage them to pull out,” said Melvin Lee, a 45-year-old protester from Tucson, Arizona. Lee said he believed that the occupation had spread an important message about the overreach of the federal government but that if it lasted much longer, he feared it could get ugly. “I want to make sure there is no violence,” he added.One of the occupiers, who declined to give his name because he said organizers had chastised him for speaking to reporters, said that he wanted to leave because he was worried about eventually getting arrested or prosecuted for his involvement.Bundy said that there were no threats about potential arrests during his meeting with the sheriff.Amid signs that leaders may be looking for an exit strategy, Ryan Bundy, Ammon’s brother, said that the militia was in contact with local ranchers who they could somehow hand over to after they leave.“They’re going to take over when we leave,” he said, acknowledging that some Harney County residents want them to depart immediately. “The community is divided and some local people don’t want us here,” he said, adding: “But there’s a large group of people that do.”LaVoy Finicum, another protester from Arizona, said he was prepared to stay for a long time but that he was also eager to reunite with his daughters. “Eventually, I want to go home,” he said.
</description>
<tags>
	oregon,us news
</tags>