<seedurl>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us
</seedurl>
<url>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2016/jan/08/oregon-militia-standoff-demands-what-comes-next
</url>
<title>
	What will happen if the Oregon militia gets its demands?
</title>
<description>
	Rare species would be endangered if Ammon Bundy and his cattle-ranching militia are permitted unfettered access to federal land, experts warnAllowing cattle to graze across swaths of federal land in Oregon, as an armed band of militia is demanding, could have devastating consequences for the area’s delicate ecosystem, experts have warned.Rare species such as the greater sage grouse that does a mating dance on federal land adjacent to the Malheur national wildlife refuge, occupied by the militia, have already been harmed by widespread cattle grazing on high-desert plains across the west.The armed militia is occupying federal land in Oregon that contains swaths of marshland, an unusual feature amid the high desert of south-eastern Oregon. It offers protection for waterfowl across its 188,000 acres, an area nearly half the size of the sprawling city of Los Angeles.The militia, a ragtag group whose leader, Ammon Bundy, comes from a Nevada family with a history of defying federal land-use rules, has a hazy wishlist that includes the release of two Oregon men, imprisoned and convicted of arson. But one of their broadest demands is to transfer more federal land to private ownership in the area.Such a change could mean a “scorched-earth” situation for wildlife, said Dale Goble, a professor and land-use expert at the University of Idaho’s College of Law, who had gone birding in the refuge.“If you’ve driven through the high desert of eastern Oregon, the distinction between private and federal [land] is often strikingly clear,” he said. Were the land to be transferred to private ownership, “the marshes and everything that attracts the migratory bird species – probably, my guess would be, used for irrigation”.The simmering tension between ranchers and the federal government is nothing new to the American west. The federal government manages enormous chunks of land, a holdover from the days of westward expansion. The federal Fish and Wildlife Service, which oversees federal endangered and threatened species, manages the Oregon refuge. Another agency called the Bureau of Land Management is also in the Oregon militia’s sights; it manages enormous western tracts and is the largest landowner in the United States.In the mid-to-late 20th century, ranchers and other groups began a movement known as the Sagebrush Rebellion to lobby for more federal land to be transferred to state control. That effort continues today, Goble said, in states like Utah and Idaho.The modern-day rebels have an even more radical wish: to transfer federal lands to private control. How that would happen is unclear, and ordinary ranchers may not have enough money to buy the land in any case, Goble said.But increased private ownership could have harsh consequences for wildlife across the west, where many plants and animals are already on the federal government’s list of threatened or endangered species.Dan Morse of the Oregon Natural Desert Association, an environmental group, said that while some species can get by with a network of connected public lands, it’s much harder to protect them when the land is a patchwork of private owners who manage their property mainly for economic gain. “For me, one of the most concerning notions is the concept that these lands need to be returned to the public,” Morse says. The land, and its benefits, “already are public”.In Oregon, waves of songbirds, sandhill cranes, long-billed curlews and other waterfowl pass through Malheur, which is a “crown jewel” of the federal refuge system, says Bob Sallinger, conservation director of the Portland Audubon Society. Some 20% of the entire population of white-faced ibises use the refuge’s lakes and waterways, he added.“Any forage, any grass, any wildflower that cows eat isn’t available for bighorn sheep, deer, elk, pronghorn, sage grouse, butterflies or other native wildlife species,” says Andy Kerr, an environmental consultant who worked on conservation and public land grazing issues near the refuge in the 1990s.“Twenty percent of all species listed under the Endangered Species Act have livestock as a factor in their decline.”The Borax Lake chub, an endangered species of fish, is found largely in the Oregon county that contains the refuge.The federal government’s record on environmental management is far from perfect, but it is considerably better than that of private landowners, Goble said. The US Fish and Wildlife Service, the agency that oversees the refuge, has a clear responsibility to manage its refuges for the sake of wildlife. The service also oversees endangered or threatened species listings, so it has a direct responsibility to protect them.The Bureau of Land Management, which oversees some 260m acres across the United States, has a less clearcut connection to threatened wildlife. It has sometimes been known as the “Bureau of Livestock and Mining” because it allows private companies and individuals to use its land for grazing (for a low fee), logging and other extraction activities. Cliven Bundy, a Nevada rancher and the father of Ammon, led an armed dispute against federal agents last year after he grazed his cattle on BLM land without paying.The BLM must consult with the wildlife service over endangered or threatened species on its lands, which should ensure at least some protections. Private landowners do not have to do such consultations, though they are prohibited from killing (or contributing to the killing of) endangered species on their property.Ranchers across the west have a different view: they see themselves as the best stewards of the land, and the federal government as imposing onerous requirements. Erin Maupin, a rancher near the refuge who visited the occupation this week, said government wildlife officials had no business controlling the land and have done a poor job of caring for the local environment. “More birds come to our ranches than here,” she said. “Non-use is misuse,” she said. “We need to play an active role in managing this land. What’s best for the species is not to do nothing.”Additional reporting by Sam Levin in Burns.
</description>
<tags>
	oregon,us news,wildlife,animals,environment
</tags>