<seedurl>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us
</seedurl>
<url>
	http://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2016/jan/09/eggs-new-us-dietary-guidelines-cholesterol
</url>
<title>
	Experts scramble to defend and denounce US dietary guidelines on eggs
</title>
<description>
	The US government has removed suggested caps on cholesterol consumption in a victory for an egg industry keen to dissociate its product from heart diseaseThe egg lobby won a major victory this month, though it was a quiet one. Nearly 30 years after the supreme court ruled that egg producers could not claim there was no risk of heart disease associated with consumption of their product, the Obama administration’s new dietary guidelines went a lot easier – potentially over easy – on eggs.  Related: Government-backed egg lobby tried to crack food startup, emails show The new guidelines have removed suggested caps on cholesterol consumption, though they do say that people eat too much protein in general. Eggs are very cholesterol-dense, and the US egg industry has long tried to shake its association with heart disease.Some physicians are skeptical of the joint decision by the US Department of Agriculture (USDA) and the Department of Health and Human Services. “The idiots,” said J David Spence of the University of Western Ontario, who has helped develop several widely used diagnostic technologies for the treatment of strokes. “It’s a big mistake.”Spence said the removal of restrictions on dietary cholesterol was the result of years of lobbying by the egg industry. After the main industry trade association was convicted by the nation’s highest court of false advertising in 1977, it – and many other producers of comestibles that had been said to have some adverse effect – began to develop studies of its own. The American Egg Board (AEB), an industry body appointed by the USDA, pursued studies that distanced its product from increased risk of heart disease and diabetes. So did the private industry body, the US Poultry & Egg Association (USPEA). The AEB also recently attacked Hampton Creek, a small startup that manufactures a supposedly healthier alternative to mayonnaise, a plant-based product called Just Mayo.Some experiments “suggest that variability of dietary cholesterol may not increase CVR [cardiovascular risk] in the context of RET [resistance exercise training],” concluded one such 2008 study, led by Texas A&M scientist Chang Woock Lee and underwritten by the USPEA. Many other, similarly funded studies offer proof that eggs are not merely reasonable but healthy.Outside industry-funded studies, thinking has changed. Last year Harvard Health Publications summed up published research with a consumer-friendly article, in which it said many of its associated scientists believed an egg a day was reasonable. The recommendation of the 2015 Dietary Guidelines Advisory Committee agreed.Meta-analyses of studies done over time on dietary cholesterol, however, seem to suggest different. A study from last year in the American Journal of Clinical Nutrition, for example, examined 40 other rigorous studies published between 1979 and 2013. It found that “dietary cholesterol statistically significantly increased both serum [blood] total cholesterol and low-density lipoprotein (LDL) cholesterol”.The discrepancy between research saying eggs do not have an effect on cholesterol and research saying they do might boil down to a single point at the bottom of the findings in that AJCN metanalysis: “Increases in LDL cholesterol were no longer statistically significant when intervention doses exceeded 900 milligrams per day.” That’s about five eggs.Put plainly, said Spence, the American diet already contains so much that could cause harm, it’s hard to measure the effect of a single potentially unhealthy food.“The problem is that in the United States diet is so bad it’s hard to prove that anything makes it worse,” said Spence. According to the American Heart Association, he said, “Fewer than 1% of all Americans have an ideal diet.”
</description>
<tags>
	eggs,food & drink industry,business
</tags>