<seedurl>
	http://www.theguardian.com/us
</seedurl>
<url>
	http://www.theguardian.com/sport/2016/jan/08/nfl-playoff-previews-chiefs-green-bay
</url>
<title>
	NFL playoff previews: Chiefs to continue winning run and Green Bay to crash out
</title>
<description>
	Kansas City haven’t won a playoff game for 22 years, but they can do so against Houston; Steelers to tame Bengals, and go for Seattle and WashingtonIt takes 256 games to whittle a starting field of 32 NFL teams down to 12 playoff contenders. And then just 11 more to pluck a Super Bowl champion from that group. If that’s good enough for the league, then it must also be good enough for us to find a winner for our annual Pick The Playoffs contest.To take part, all you need to do is make your picks for each week’s games in the comments section below. I will post the overall standings in the comments section of next week’s blog. We will crown a champion at the end of Super Bowl 50, as well as combining the scores with our regular season Pick Six contest to find our overall gold medalist for 2015-16. Speaking of which, I can now reveal that we had a three-way tie atop the Pick Six this year. Raise your glasses, doff your caps, and generally stand in awe of goodfella493, Nostradamus and Uma Blue – each of whom finished the regular season with 60 correct predictions from a possible 102. A notably lower score than last year’s winners required, but that is a mark of how unpredictable this season has been. Will the playoffs prove similarly perplexing? There’s only one way to find out. If you had named this as a potential playoff matchup at the end of October, you might have been laughed out of town. Back then, Kansas City and Houston had identical 2-5 records, and each was ranked by the bookies as a 200-1 shot to win the Super Bowl. But the Chiefs have not lost a game since, while the Texans have only dropped two. On form alone, these look like two of the more dangerous teams entering the postseason. Each can count on a formidable defense. JJ Watt and the Texans have surrendered just 12.7 points per game since week eight, but the Chiefs were not far behind on 12.8. Kansas City, though, was missing its top pass rusher – Justin Houston – for the past five. He returned to practice this week and might make a significant impact against opponents who just lost starting left tackle Duane Brown to a quad injury. That, though, is not the only reason I am leaning the Chiefs’ way. They have not won a playoff game for 22 years but the superstitious among you might already have spotted that the last time they did so, it was with a former San Francisco 49er at quarterback. Alex Smith is no Joe Montana, but he is an underestimated player who brings valuable experience to this stage. He led the 49ers to an NFC title game in 2011 and might have gone one further if he had been given the chance a year later. In three career playoff games, he has thrown nine touchdowns and no interceptions. Between him and Brian Hoyer, there’s no question who I would want behind center with a game on the line. Chiefs to winWere it not for injuries, either of these teams might have entered the postseason as a Super Bowl favourite. It is to the Steelers’ immense credit that they have made it this far at all, despite doing without one of the league’s best running backs, Le’Veon Bell, from week six onwards, as well as starting quarterback Ben Roethlisberger for four games in the middle of the season. The Bengals were already well on their way to an AFC North title before they lost their own signal caller, Andy Dalton, and they too have shown a certain resilience to win two of the three games started by his backup AJ McCarron so far. Both teams have clearly been compromised, but for this weekend, the only question that matters is which one of them can cope better with the adversity.It is the uncertain status of Bell’s replacement that has really left Pittsburgh in a bind. DeAngelo Williams averaged a solid 4.5 yards per carry in Bell’s absence, but suffered a foot injury of his own against Cleveland in week 17 and (at time of writing) has not practiced since. The next man up, Fitzgerald Toussaint, managed just 2.0 yards per attempt against the Browns’ 30th-ranked rush defense. The Steelers need at least the threat of a running game to keep their opponents honest on Saturday. Although they won in Cincinnati last month, Roethlisberger has found the going tough in both meetings with the Bengals this season – throwing a combined one touchdown and four interceptions. And yet, I still find myself leaning his way. McCarron has been solid so far, going without a pick in his four starts, but he will be under pressure to do more than just play it safe against a Steelers team that put up the fourth-most points in the regular season. Steelers to winSo this is the Vikings’ reward for beating Green Bay in week 17: a rematch against the Seattle team that steamrollered them 38-7 in Minnesota last month. A team which just crushed the previously red-hot Cardinals 36-6 in Arizona, as well. A No6 seed could hardly look any scarier than the Seahawks do now. Yes, they have had some less impressive games along the way to a 10-6 record, but often those have been influenced by injury or – at the start of the season – Kam Chancellor’s hold-out on defense. Seattle’s only loss in the last seven weeks came against a Rams team that simply seems to have its number. And even then, the Seahawks played that game without Marshawn Lynch or Chancellor – both of whom were back at practice on Wednesday and are expected to play this weekend. Are the Vikings capable of beating these opponents? Sure, but only if they can make this a low-scoring game. The Seahawks gave up the fewest points in the regular season for the fourth year running (even more remarkable when you consider that their schedule included appointments with the Bengals, Panthers, Steelers and Cardinals – twice – and that Chancellor missed a total of five games) and for all the strides made by Teddy Bridgewater, I simply do not see him being the man to blow them open. That puts the onus on Minnesota’s defense to slow down Russell Wilson, at a time when he is playing the best football of his career. He has thrown for 24 touchdowns and just a single pick over the past seven weeks. If I’m being honest, I don’t foresee the Vikings having much success on this side of the ball, either. Seahawks to winOn balance, I do think that Green Bay gained a more favourable playoff matchup by finishing as runners-up in the NFC North. Washington, even at FedEx field, is a less daunting opponent than Seattle right now. But the Packers are not in a position to take anyone lightly, least of all a team that has won four straight and five of its last six. Somewhere along the way to a division title, Kirk Cousins matured into a bona fide starting quarterback – and a pretty darn good one, at that. Specifically, the metamorphosis can be pegged pretty closely to the “You Like That” game against Tampa Bay. As noted by ESPN, Cousins had thrown 24 touchdowns and 27 interceptions in his career prior to that game. His 23 scores since – achieved on fewer than half as many passing attempts – have come at a cost of just three picks. He still has a long way to go to prove himself the equal of Aaron Rodgers, but unlike his Green Bay counterpart, Cousins can count on a productive supporting cast. Jordan Reed has finally stayed healthy long enough to emerge as one of the NFL’s best pass-catching tight ends. The Packers have failed to find any such reliable outlet in Jordy Nelson’s absence. Rodgers has seen more passes dropped than any other quarterback in the league. A depleted Washington secondary might well present a few opportunities, but it is no guarantee that Rodgers – also the second-most sacked quarterback this season – will be given time to exploit them. I can scarcely believe I am writing this, but the way that Green Bay’s offense has misfired lately, I fear they may struggle to keep up. Washington to win
</description>
<tags>
	sport,nfl,us sports,kansas city chiefs,houston texans,pittsburgh steelers,cincinnati bengals,seattle seahawks,minnesota vikings,green bay packers,washington (nfl team)
</tags>