<seedurl>
	http://www.foxnews.com/
</seedurl>
<url>
	http://www.foxnews.com/leisure/2016/01/08/5-things-need-to-know-about-scott-disick-new-place-in-hidden-hills/
</url>
<title>
	5 Things You Need to Know About Scott Disick's New Place in Hidden Hills
</title>
<description>
	Scott Disick has a new home to call his own. Kourtney Kardashian's ex (and father to their three kids) has set up new digs, according to Radar Online. Here's the scoop on the new place.1. It's not a bachelor pad -- it's a dad padDisick's three kids with Kardashian will feel right at home in this Hidden Hills, CA, dream home. The newly renovated seven-bedroom, Cape Cod -- style residence includes a family room downstairs and a bonus loft in the children's wing upstairs, according to the listing. The home is located at the end of a kid-friendly cul-de-sac. -- -- -- 2. OK, it's kind of a swinging place, too The Lord can get in touch with his wild side thanks to huge living and dining rooms, which open up to each other for casual entertaining. And although he's on the wagon, there is adjacent refrigerated wine storage for guests. Sliding walls of glass mean party people can spill out to the lushly landscaped backyard. -- -- -- 3. Master of the master suiteThe master suite is suited for the man of the house, with a balcony, marble bath, and giant closets. There's also a separate guest suite, which is ideal for visitors or staff. -- -- -- 4. Pricey, but lots of amenitiesDisick paid a hair under $6 million for the home. Built in 1975, the property recently went through an expansion and remodel. High-end touches include a brand-new chef's kitchen with stone counters and stainless-steel appliances, walls of windows, and an outdoor paradise of lawns, patios, a fire pit, a pool and spa, and a basketball court. -- -- -- 5. It's close to the Kardashian clanDisick and Kardashian's on-again, off-again relationship is off, for now. For the time being, having the family as neighbors will have to suffice.
</description>
<tags>
	bachelor pad,cape cod,kourtney kardashian,basketball court
</tags>